Unknown: This today is a
background on open licenses
specifically for with
information that might be
helpful for your open life
science projects. Disclaimer
number one, I'm not a lawyer.
You'll hear that again during
the talk. So, I'm going to keep
going if everything's okay,
audio video. Okay, so I'm
Christine Rogers, I see a few
people who know me already on
this call. So shout out to my
Montreal, people like Kendra and
Sam gays crew. I'm part of that
open science ecosystem based in
Montreal. Personally, I'm at
McGill University at the
Montreal Neurological Institute,
which is the largest academic
Open Science Research Institute
going. And, specifically, I'm a
Data Manager, research research
project officer on a number of
open science projects and
initiatives. Because I work for
the Loris databasing group, we
make an open source platform,
that's basically data tool
databasing, data sharing for
neuroscience research. And it's
also used in a lot of open
science initiatives. So that's
my context. I have also been a
part of the open lifesigns
cohort that started in January,
very happy to be
back.
And I focused in that phase on
adoptability metrics and support
for open source research
software. I'm also involved in
some of Google's open source
programs in terms of mentoring
for Google Summer of Code, and
Google season docs this fall,
and if anyone wants to connect
with me, you can reach me on
Twitter, my handle is at the
bottom of the slide, and I will
take it from there. So today
we're talking about licensing.
The purpose of the presentation,
for the context of the open Life
Science program is that licenses
are going to allow you and
anyone to use, remix and share
what you're doing on your
project. The outcome of today
and under the exercises you're
going through today is that your
project is going to be openly
licensed for use for re mixing
and for sharing. Today we're
doing a short presentation,
followed by discussion with some
practical steps to help you work
towards adding an open license
to your work. The steps are
really simple, the thinking
behind it is worth taking a
moment to go over. So that's the
plan for today. Am I still good
on the audio visual front? Okay,
great. I just have to figure out
what to click.
About. There you go. Yeah. Okay.
So how does this fit into the
open leadership framework? Let's
start there. The context of the
open leadership framework is
that open leaders will design
and build projects that empower
others to collaborate within
inclusive communities. And with
licensing, when you think of
licensing you don't really think
of empowering, you think of
restricting, I think is terms of
everyone's experience with user
licenses would be a really
familiar example. For example, a
lot of people know MATLAB in
terms of the context that it's
available free for use for
academia. But if you're trying
to use the context of company,
or privately, suddenly, the
license costs a lot of money. So
user licenses are one
perspective, we're going to flip
the script today, because from
your point of view, as a creator
of a project, you're looking to
add a license to your project,
that's going to tell others,
what they're free to do with
your work, how they can share
it, reproduce it, adapt it, and
what their rights and
obligations are in that respect.
And that also gives you as the
creator the protection of having
those clearly in place, having
that framework, but at the same
time, being able to share what
you've produced really openly
once that is in place. So that's
how licenses can be a powerful
tool for sharing. And that's how
they also fit into the grid for
the open leadership framework.
under the category of build for
sharing, licensing is something
that really enables you to share
your work as you build out your
project. There's a few key
aspects to licensing. I'm not an
expert. I'm not a lawyer, I'm
not your lawyer. But we're going
to continue on this basis with a
bit of background for truly open
licenses, I think they all have
the common elements about use
modification and sharing of
software. So use is just who can
use the work and for what
purpose, whether it's commercial
or research, only modification
can that work be modified, who
can modify it for what purpose
and then sharing so if If you
make a modification to work, can
you share what you produce with
other people? And how? And can
you redistribute the original
also, there's a definition of
open source down below. And I'm
going to avoid the debate on
what open source isn't is not
today and skip ahead to what you
guys need to know about
licensing. So under those three
common elements of truly open
licensing, the first part where
it's important to pay attention
to how this impacts you is
attribution. So most open
licenses will require others to
credit the authors or copyright
holders of the work. That's a
pretty common thing that a lot
of people are used to examples
are with the Creative Commons bi
license, and almost all the
other licenses, you need to
attribute the work when you use
it. To the original authors.
This is really common, if he's a
photo, for example, you're going
to want to credit the source.
There's also a type of license
that says there's no attribution
to be made. And that's a cc zero
license, which says it's
something is effectively in the
public domain and is actually no
copyright holder. So moving on
from attribution. The next
important thing is distribution.
So when you when you're
distributing something to the
original or something that you
modified, what are your rights
and obligations. So the two main
types of open licensing aspects
are non copyleft and copyleft.
Starting with copyleft, this is
a permissive non reciprocal
license. The important point is
that it's an open license that
does not require derivative
works to be shared using the
same license. Examples of the CC
by license MIT BSD and AAPL 2.0
license. On the other hand, you
have copyleft licenses, these
are reciprocal or viral
licenses. And the idea is that
an open license, it's an open
license that requires all
derivative works to be shared
with the same license. So
anything downstream of the
original code or product needs
to be shared using the same
license. So in that sense,
you're restricted to the same
conditions. So examples of that
are the CC by sa license GPL,
v3, which is really common in
the Unix community, and or Linux
Mint, I should say. Then MPL
2.0. So just a bit more context
about these two aspects, what
does it mean to require
derivative works to be shared
with the same license or not?
In my context, we make an open
source tool. And we allow people
afford to freely make their own
adaptations, and then use that
for their own purposes. But the
moment that they want to share
what they've done features,
they've added maybe domain
specific tools or content in
there, the moment they want to
share that with, let's say,
their colleagues in the same
field or someone else. Our
license is a GPL three, which is
a copyleft license, and it's
governs them. So we've
effectively required them to
contribute their modifications
back to the community. And the
idea with that is that anything
open needs to stay open. So the
good side is that the community
benefits, that's the idea. The
downside to think about with
copyleft is that it means that
it might actually be a
deterrent, in some cases, from
letting people use it for
private use, because it can't go
very far without them being
obligated to openly share it. On
the other hand, copyleft also
has the benefit that money for
that statement, non copyleft,
some licenses actually enable
people to take your work and
make their own version. And
technically they could actually
sell that version that they
modify. So that's something to
keep in mind with non copyleft
licenses. There's many things to
look at on both sides. But
that's kind of the context in
which these things are
important. So moving on, for in
terms of patent clauses, most
modern open source software
licensing Do you contain a
clause that is designed to
prevent people from using patent
law to take away open source
rights? That's called patent
snapback and that means that the
patent rights sort of by default
revert to the person who
released it. Examples of this
are NPL, AAPL and GPL v3.
Sometimes this isn't applicable
and older licenses like MIT and
BSD, but I don't think that
would be a concern for people
applying licenses here
necessarily.
In terms of how to
apply a license, it's actually
very simple. If you're used
GitHub, which I think this
program still is as a default
tool, then you GitHub has a
really easy, it's not even a
workflow. It's like a prompt.
When you start a new project to
add a license, you as you can
see from the slide, it's a drop
down that you just select what
kind of license you want to use.
So couldn't be easier to
actually apply it on your file.
And it's typically in a file
called license or licensed dot
txt, often all caps you stick it
in the main directory of your
project, and GitHub will do that
for you. So also, in terms of
how to apply a license, beyond
just putting the file in your
repository, there are specific
instructions, you need to follow
on certain licenses, details are
available at those links, choose
license, comm
creativecommons.org, those links
will appear again on the last
slide. So we'll come back to
these resources. Also good to
know is that you can have
multiple licenses within a
single project, some for content
and some for the actual software
part, just as long as you're
clear about which goes on which
and that's typically done in the
readme of your project. Details
on copyleft, non copyleft,
patent snapback older licenses
with no patent clause, versus
attribution and no attribution
is broken down here in this
table. There's, you know, choose
a license comm is a great
resource for choosing licenses
for software for content, people
might gravitate towards the
Creative Commons licensing. And
then I'm gonna put a caveat at
the bottom for data, some people
use csio. I am not going to go
into that today. But I just want
to say like from my research
context, data licensing and data
sharing is very special and very
tricky. There are a lot of
considerations. For some of you
who might be doing a survey for
your project, you might include
one, including presentation
consideration, such as
participant consent, and the
ethics of data sharing, if
you're collecting data, whether
the data your data can use for
commercial purposes, or you just
want to use for research
purposes and what that means. So
licensing data as a whole other
fields, and I'll leave that sort
of out of the scope of today's
talk. If anyone's doing a
hardware project just for fun on
the side hardware licenses are
also another specialty. So those
things are slightly out of the
scope today, but still
definitely relevant domains. So
coming to the end, here are some
links for further reading. There
are some books, there are some
guides. And one thing I would
advise is that when you're
choosing a license, don't go to
the Wikipedia page. Yo, this was
the meme I was gonna make for
you don't go to Wikipedia page,
do actually look around in your
community that you're going to
release your project into that's
the code or the the program or
framework or the data that
you're that you're working
towards, what's the community
that's going to use it and
modify and adapt it and take it
further and what licensing is
the norm or common practice
there. Because you are also
signaling kind of like the
values of your project through
the licensing that you use. And
you want to use as much as
possible a license that people
are comfortable with, and
conforms with the standards that
that that are prevalent in the
community that you're actually
trying to attract and build
with. Okay, and then at the
bottom to the license. Zilla,
open leadership actually has its
own page on licensing. So there
have been a summary there. And
then those links again for
chooser, license calm, which is
kind of like choose your own
adventure, explore licensing,
and creative commons.org are
great resources for getting
started on this licensing
adventure. So I hope that helps
with the covering some content
for licensing. And that's my
talk today.