Unknown: I'm here to talk to you
a about creating a positive
culture for contribution and
collaboration for your open
projects. And we will
specifically be looking at
making a contributing guide and
a code of conduct. So let's get
going. And we'll try this
quickly. So I am Lily, and I'm a
product manager for the
frictionless data project, which
is an open source project. And I
work at the Open Knowledge
Foundation. And you can also
follow me on Twitter. So what is
a project culture, the culture
is very important to think about
when you're working on an open
project, because it isn't just
you that's working on this.
Ideally, you want to be creating
a community. And we've just
heard a little bit about this,
like why you would be creating a
readme document. Part of that is
to help build up your community.
And a healthy project culture
has a healthy community, meaning
it has diverse members that you
know, have different backgrounds
and ideas and talents that can
help build your community. So to
help build and guide your
culture, there's a few things
you need to keep in mind. One is
that it's a conscious decision
that you as a leader need to
make. And what I mean by that is
that a culture will build itself
within your project. Regardless
of whether or not you build it,
it's like it will still happen.
But for it to be the culture
that you want to build, you need
to make some decisions, and help
it build according to your
values. So you need to identify
what your values are. And that
includes things like how should
people behave that are part of
this? Okay, here is a picture
example of things to think about
for your project culture. So
this is an XKCD. We're also just
talking about, can I load it up
on your laptop sugar, oh, just
hit both Shift keys to change
over to Qwerty, perhaps like is
Ctrl spacebar caps lock in to
fear scroll means through time
instead of space. And that dot
with the subtitle saying, once
I've used a computer for a while
no one else will ever use it
again. And this is showing you
that the choices that you make
determine who can or can't also
use your project. The project
culture is more than just its
goals. It's also things like the
language, shared set of norms,
your expectations and your
people's expectations, the tools
that you choose to use, and
things like how decisions are
made, and the project's
identity. So how can you build
your projects culture? Two ways
we're going to talk about today
are using clear contributor
guidelines and a code of conduct
that importantly, is
enforceable. So what is a
community? This image was on the
slides, and I thought it was so
cute. And I really like it,
because it shows that you know,
a community is about different
worlds animals here, but
different people, different
users, and how they all interact
together. And maybe you know,
one part of the community is the
base, like the thing that's
keeping everyone warm. But there
are other members of the
community that also have
different goals. And they have
different reasons for being part
of the community. So it's
important to understand why
people are part of the community
and what they gain from it, and
what they can get. What is
contribution? attribution is a
vital part of teamwork. And they
contributions come in many
different forms. And we'll talk
about those a little bit here.
And that they can be like
writing code, writing,
documentation, editing, giving
ideas, project management,
there's all sorts of things that
team members can do to help the
team as a whole. on GitHub,
there are several ways you can
look at contributors and
contributors is a specific term
that gets abuses. And for
instance, this is from the
frictionless data project. They
work on one of our repositories,
we have 23 contributors. So on
your GitHub projects, you will
also see how many contributors
you have.
So a good way that everyone, all
of your projects should have a
contributing document. And you
can do this on GitHub. It's
called a contributing.md. So
it's a markdown document. And
here's an example of one from
one of our repositories, and so
it has some general guidelines
and this specific document goes
on for a long time that it tells
you in all potential users, how
they can help. So it gives you
instructions for like how to
write the code, according to the
style guide. And it also tells
you things like, the language
that is most commonly used, and
it can give tips for beginners.
And it will tell you things
like, you know, this is the
software that we use. And here's
where you can go to find help.
So everyone should create a
contributing.md file. And there
are I think there's lots of
examples, I think, in the notes
as well for these. Okay, so why
and what contributing, MD tells
you the structure of
contributions, it provides
guidelines, and a standard
style. And it's also used to
improve efficiency. So people
don't have to ask the leader
over and over again, you know,
how can I contribute, you can
point them to this guide. And
it's a great way to involve new
people and build up your
community. There are different
people that you need to consider
when making this contributors
guide, the owners, which would
be you know, most of you, owners
of the organization, or project,
all of the contributors, which
are all members that have done
something to help. And then the
consumers are the users of the
project. And, you know,
sometimes people will fall in
all three of these categories.
Okay, you can also create a
contributors or community page
on your website, if you have a
project website that's different
from the GitHub. And this is a
nice example from the
carpentries. And I'll just leave
that there for you guys to look
through later. But it has a lot
of great detail. Alright, so now
we're going to talk about code
of contracts. And why it's
important to have a code of
conduct. And we talked about
this a little bit already, but
your project or route will
really flourish with a diverse
community. But I skipped on,
hold on, you know, I think I'm
just going in the opposite
direction. Okay, but what if
something happens, if something
happens, you need to have a code
of conduct. A Code of Conduct is
a set of rules that outline the
social norms, rules and
responsibilities of an
individual project, party or
organization. And it's commonly
abbreviated as a CRC. So a lot
of people ask me, do you really
need a CRC? Yes, is the short
answer. But why a code of
conduct invites people to your
project, it sets clear
expectations for your community
members. And it tells
contributors that you care about
your community, and that you
care about creating a welcoming
space for everyone. Here's some
links to some examples of code
of conduct. And I especially
like the Python code of conduct,
it is the most thorough code of
conduct that I think I've ever
seen. And I reference it all of
the time. So I really recommend
the Python code of here's an
example from the CSB con put of
conduct which I helped write
this while earlier this year
when we went to a virtual
conference. And it has a lot of
the basic parts of the code of
conduct, it outlines who the
Code of Conduct is for what kind
of behavior is expected, what
kind of behavior is not allowed,
and importantly, the enforcement
and reporting that would occur
if there's a breach of the code
of conduct. So a code of conduct
is not just a box item. And a
lot of people will create one
say, oh, we're done. But you
actually aren't gun, it's really
important to make sure that your
code of conduct has both
enforcement and reporting
included in and you need to have
specific ways that it's clear to
people how they can report and
who they are reporting to. And
many of you probably heard this,
I think yo was mentioning the
Code of Conduct earlier, and
went through a lot of details.
So, you know, no one likes a
code of conduct is also a great
example.
Okay, so getting started, how do
you start with your code of
conduct, you should brainstorm
some core words that represent
your community values. And then
think about behaviors that you
want to encourage or discourage.
Think through the process for
incidents and complaints. And
then also think about the
consequences for people that
actually Outside of these norms
that are defined, and of course,
you have to understand and
accept your role as a project
lead. And if you are
uncomfortable or unsure about
how to deal with reports, reach
out to your community and ask
for help and support. So tips
and takeaways, encourage and
reward good practice, designate
the code of conduct and safety
committee to help you with this.
Make sure your code of conduct
is posted visible and clear and
communicated to your
contributors and use an existing
code of conduct. Many of them
are openly licensed, which you
just learned about and you can
reuse them.