Unknown: My background is in
biology actually. So that I
won't go into these details,
I'll just jump right in and
mention this kind of publication
that was back in 2016, about a
fair guiding principle for the
management of scientific data.
And as Amy was mentioning, this,
this a set of this is an acronym
basically, that outlines the
kind of key things that you need
to think about when you try to
release the data, or at least
handle the data that you're
producing in your daily, daily
life. And this has been endorsed
by a number of people, you can
see the lifestyle authors,
scanning, people doing research,
scientific, publishing, funding
agencies and policy really, it
was a cross section of all the
players. And and because they
wanted to raise this kind of
alarm, call call alarm, but in a
way for for improving the way
things were done and why does it
matter. So, basically, the main,
the main purpose is to make sure
that the data can be used by
machines, because or into the
production of data at such a
scale. Now, we need to be able
to find data, which means that
the data set can be uniquely
identified, they can be given a
unique resolvable and stable
identifier. This allows people
to retrieve and collect data.
And then what is really
important in terms of
discoverability is that you need
to describe the data with enough
descriptors, the metadata,
basically, and these sets of
descriptors need to be agreed by
your community, because we will
be different, we have got domain
of expertise. And in order to
make things understood by the
community, we need to agree on
the kind of common language, we
also need to think about how to
access the data. This means that
so far doesn't mean necessarily
that everything is open and
pretty available. It just tells
you that you should provide
information, and how what are
the conditions of access, if you
don't want to access you have to
tell it to tell people that
Okay, there is an embargo, for
instance, then you need to reuse
terminologies, ideally, and
again, we go back to this in a
moment, just simply to make sure
that there is no ambiguity. But
when you data about what you
actually meant with it, we need
to provide detailed provenance
information so that again, this
allows people to understand what
has been done, and how did it I
was generated. And all you need
to allow people to be clear,
completely clear about what are
the conditional reuse. This is
where the licensing issue come
into play. And this allows you
to make sure that your data set
is reusable. Or at least you
describe what under which
condition is that a sets are
allowed for for consumption. So
in a way, this comes into a
backdrop of information between
the gap between data generation
and drivability, just want to
tell you about the same AI
programs as European initiatives
that brings pharma, industry and
academic to produce to scan and
produce research data on a
variety of projects, massive,
it's been running since 2008,
I'd say the investment is huge,
you can see the number of
publications. But again, you
have to, to think about this
publication of scientific data,
typically, in principle back in
2016. That was in a way
complaint while calling for data
to be fair. And in 2013, there
was a publication again, by the
EU trying to scan I understand
what is the cost of not having
data in a fair shake. So that it
gives you the links to these
documents. But the take home
message is that in the red, in
the spy here in the red patch is
the cost of in a waste on the
expenditure of the data, not
being managed, but on the other
side is the missed opportunity.
Like it's almost it's, it's as
if it's like 150% of that profit
figure. It represents the missed
opportunities of not making the
data available, I mean, the lack
of meaning and things. And so
this is the impact on
innovation, you can have the
absence of data, this kind of
dark matter, we know that data
is around, but we can see it.
And this is why the AMA decided
to to fund a project which was
called surplus to see to
understand will improve the
processes of releasing data. So
I'm trying to go for an analogy
of, of cooking in a way and I
call it the empty fridge
problem. Let's take the
political situation where your
country is about to go in
lockdown. And and you want to
cook something but your fridge
looks like this. And of course
you want to go to shops, but the
shops basically you can't find
them because there is no way to
know where the shops are. And if
you happen to find a store you
when you look at the supplies,
they look like this. And of
course then it's a big mess if
you want to reuse anything to
prepare the toy your favorite
meal because you have no idea of
what is the
so
so really the notion
verification is to, is to be put
labels on all these scans that
we find and make them really
meaningful. So that basically
applying a set of metadata is
already interesting, you can
have information about what is
the content of the scan. And
maybe there are things that you
don't like to see in the scan.
And so you don't want to do
about it at all. And you've got
to composition you've got volume
going to price, you're gonna
sell number, these kind of
things that allow you to make a
decision whether you want to use
or not, that particular element.
So if you're lucky enough to
have to have access to this
delicacy, spaghetti bolognaise
in the can, you're very pleased
to to have information about the
metadata that you can have, it
gives you a good insight into
whether it selfie or not at all,
and what kind of energy you get.
And this is in a way on the
label. But is it really what it
says? So sometimes it's good to
have a certification and
organization to control bodies
in the campus survey, that may
be you know, it's organic,
really, it's not contain it
doesn't contain some GMO
organisms, you should want to
want to eat them. So really,
it's important to trust but
always check. And you may know
that there was a scandal a few
years back, that in some of
these scans, even though they
claim to be beef, they were
actually it was horse meat. And
of course, this is this is not
right. So it's about checking,
it's about controlling, it's
about asserting that things are
okay. So in the context of data
science, this is really the
backdrop of fair competence was
making, you know, the kind of
confidence crisis that we
identified, I put up a number of
references here, just to let you
know about the problems that we
faced. But as machine learning
comes into play, this is an
important of data ready nice to
make sure that the data that
goes into these algorithms is of
good quality. So good training
can occur. And the data that is
published is, is can be really a
mine effectively by scientist.
So there are two aspects of
turning phone to read it, it's
really to make sure that we have
the tools, the infrastructures,
the services, that we train
people to get familiar with
those tools, but also that we
have the standards, you know, I
was mentioning, again, what kind
of metadata descriptors you can
have in the can. This is what we
call standards, as well. And
this is really a matter of
social and technical agreement,
we need to protect and agree on
conversion. And this is this is
hard. But I guess it's really
important, no longer an option,
we have to do it. So there are
tools and resources to help you
in in surveying the different
domains, you will, you may have
different backgrounds, and you
may operate in very different
fields. But still, there are
three things that you will be
dealing with four data formats,
that are structures,
terminologies, and guidelines
and identify errors. These are,
I'm just showing a few examples.
In the world of stellar
developing observations, such
DHL seven, ISO w three CCGs can
do clinical domain, for
instance. But also grassroots
standards, like the genomic
standard Consortium, Alliance
yupo psi, the triple aim is
fortune and began health. And in
order to help you navigate that
sea of standards, you can point
go to fairsharing.org, that will
give you an overview, relation
between standards that are based
in policies that will have
somehow navigate the sea of
standards and make sure that for
your domain, you can find the
relevant resources that are
meaningful for you to establish
a data management plan. So on of
course, I mentioned evaluation.
So there are tools that have
been developed, such as the fare
evaluator that allows you to
give it an identifier to the
service, and it will run a set
of questions or set of checks
and give you a report. This is
in development. Of course, this
is the early days. But this is
also to indicate that the kind
of framework and infrastructure
they do exist to do to do this
kind of fair data. So I will
finish really with two slides. I
hope I didn't overshoot too
much. But let's let's take an
example of treating that
presentation as a data set. So
the key thing is that what could
you do this, what could you use
as a service to just do first
step verification, you could use
try to use the nudo, which is
the CERN repos repository. So I
could just upload login to this
website, I should have an orchid
ID, which is a unique identifier
for me, I hope you all have an
orchid ID that will help in the
process. First thing I could do
is to stick the file of this
presentation in this middle by
uploading it
then I need to decide what kind
of set asides it is what kind of
whether it's a presentation or
pure data set so you can be of
choice. Then moving on. I can
provide some data metadata,
publication title, basically,
but also you can see already can
listing authors and it's
integrated with arcade already.
So this is why I was mentioning
it's quite cool to have an
arcade. It's a persistent
identity, resolvable identifier
for your identity and connects
with those. And you can reserve
a DUI which would be a unique
identifier Again, it was
horrible for your MC for the
metadata about your data set.
Moving on, you can go back to
the terminal access. So you can
be accessibility, you can
describe it. And again, I insist
It doesn't mean to be fair, that
doesn't mean they have to be
open, you can set an embargo.
And the tool that I'm showing
you allows us just to do that,
you have to select the license.
That's I think, important. We
because this is about reuse, and
to be unambiguous about that.
And finally, I wanted to show
you that the tool allows you to
connect your funding sources,
it's always good to acknowledge
the funding agencies, because
they can also assess what you
actually have produced. And it's
also give visibility to all your
work. So you can do that with
the UI with the user interface
that I just showed. But you can
also do that, programmatically.
I've done. The address to the
fare cookbook that we are
developing on a fare plus, which
allows you to we should give you
a description of how to do that
with a Python script, provided
you have the API keys through
service. And yes, this is you
can see the message that is
passed to the to the by the
tool, you will have information
about the orchid ID obviously
embedded and i think that's
that's what I wanted to tell you
about to federate and give you
an example. I hope I didn't
overshoot too much. Thank you
for your attention.