Unknown: Hi, everyone, and
thanks for the very kind
patient. So as Amy said, The
plan is to give some insights
about first software. And I'll
try to be more specific about
various software. Because in my
mind, sort of, let's, let's go a
bit deeper. And before we start,
I want to highlight the sort of
a comment that I I really take
to heart. I, there's a lot of
focus on on for data, especially
if you look at different funding
opportunities in recent years,
policies as well. But I'm very
in favor of the of this quote
that says that data implies
software, because it doesn't
make sense to, to sit around a
hoard of really well done data,
but don't really have anything
to do with them. So not lacking
the tools to actually do
something with this really
awesome data. So this leads me
to a point that if you look at
software, especially over the
past 1015 years, even possibly
more research really relies on
software, and I'm using here, a
study done by SSI, just a few
years ago, the software
synthesis, they will Institute
in UK, about the relies on
software. So you can see that
92% of various community and
regularly uses research software
and almost 70% would not be
possible to do their actual work
without the software if the
software is not available. So
software is actually a key part.
At the same time, if you look at
the researcher, as an
individual, at this state of
pleased, they need to worry
about how to deal with data, how
to ensure that their data is
collected, collected properly,
it's fair to actually do the
analysis. Occasionally, if not
always developed the software do
that, ensure that the software
and all the research is
reproducible, and sort of this
can be done in fruitful
operations. And this is just the
tip of the iceberg if you don't
want to go more into depth. So,
the idea here is to remove
basically one of the things to
worry about, and in my mind
would be to resolve the software
aspects. So, as I said, this
software is pretty much
everywhere. So if you look at
any particular point in this
lifecycle, you have software
there from the lead generation
to how to the net analysis, how
to the application to do the
resource planning, all those
imply in some sense, some
software, but that takes place.
But and here where the fair
aspects come in, and research
software cannot be as easily
addressed as data. So if you
take a few principles, you
cannot consider that software is
basically there and sort of
apply them as they are. They do
have some similarities. And one
of them being that either,
neither are commonly cited. So
this is one thing to bear in
mind. But both teams have have
multiple versions both have
licenses, I have a question mark
there, because I will be
addressing this shortly in terms
of similarities. And they have
something that they are sort of
fairly similar in the sense that
both can be used as the basis
for several other things to to
be built on top. And they have
some big reliance on existing
hardware, software and so forth.
But there we have also a lot of
differences. So if you look at
the at the at the dependency,
it's only beta is much more
straightforward in terms of
dependencies and software
usually have a much larger and
more complex set of dependencies
to deal with. And, and when you
talk about reuse. And if you
start addressing this for
software, then we have a whole
different set of ours to deal
with like rerun, reuse, re
execute, repeat, reproduce,
extend. So all those are
different parts of the reuse
term, if you want to go that
way. And finally, as opposed to
the data, and research software
tends to be used more
efficiently in terms of
workflows. So you have piece of
software that sort of for one
after the other. So what we did
is just a year ago or a couple
of years ago, we started working
on how to re investigate or re
identify the first principle for
for software.
We started with a definition of
software being something that is
used generate process or analyze
the results that you intend to
have in rotation, which in my
mind has a big question mark on
the side but well, it's
something that basically
everyone can see. Sort of agree
with as a baseline. But then we
have many for many purposes of
indecision tunnels. So there's a
whole different set of things to
discuss. But and now we'll
connect also to one of the
earlier points of was raised in
today's call. Traditional
research software is often
created as a open source
software. So it's, it has a very
clear overlap with F OSS, but
the same time, when you're
dealing with fair, you don't
necessarily imply that it's,
it's, it's it's free and open
source. And so there is one
decision to to bear in mind.
Ideally, we want everything to
be free and open source. But at
the same time, the four
principles per se, do not imply
This is pretty glass. So for the
next couple of slides, I'll
really, really go fast through
the different principles s, the
suggestion is to re assess them
for for use of software. So if
you go find the ability, on the
top, I have the original
principles, and if you look them
up, and then you have what is
happening to the software case.
So when you're talking about to
find the ability, the metadata
are mainly applicable to
themselves. It's it's in that
context, but the subject that is
identification can be both
intrinsic and external. So how
to connect them with with
external databases and
registries. And again, when
dealing with registries and how
you want your insert to be
finable, and I will move away
from the GitHub and only focus
on on the metadata themselves.
You need to considered how there
are specialized registry. So
there are some that are very
specific for use of software
enabled for particular domains.
And there is no one cut all
register that you can we can use
in this context, and you need to
be aware of that. And also
should talk about describing
with Rick's metadata you're in
software, usually, you often use
semantic versioning. So there is
an intrinsic description of how
this is described. And the
accessibility part is roughly
the same. For both data and vs
software, there are minor
technicalities to be addressed.
But largely because the
accessibility is relying on the
metadata. In particular, it's
easy enough to to implement and
to completely transfer to
software and moving to the
interoperability, visibly
rejigger reusability. Sorry.
This is where things come a bit
more complex for
interoperability for data, then
the main concept is to use to
use the common vocabularies and
have the references standard
metadata. However, when we are
talking about interoperability
for software, and these points
can be easily addressed. But
when you're talking about
interoperable software software
that can sort of interoperate,
what does it imply? Are we
talking about how to connect
different pieces of software to
each other? Or are we talking on
how the data goes into a suffer?
reflect on that? Are we talking
about Sandra for Beethoven? So
there is a a bit of a gray area
there on how you need to define
Mitra bevelled. And we had some
suggestions in that context as
well. Same with regions
available. So we are talking
about having rich weather data
for data and licensing and
detailed provenance. So for
sure, we're talking about
dependencies and licenses for
software, this is absolutely
critical to to include in order
to be reusable. But at the same
time, you might also need
documentation. What are the use
cases that do exist? How, how
can we ensure that you can
actually use something it's not
just a piece of code that has a
license and a reasoning of the
dependencies. And finally, as I
said before, reusability is a
rather broad term, when we talk
about software, we talk about
rerun or reuse or produce. So
what is the art part and
occasionally, you might have
come across fair rrrr or
different ranges so far in
literature trying to address
exactly this particular case.
And so this is sort of a first
attempt that happened. Again, as
I said about a year ago, it was
an attempt to interpret the four
principles as they are right
now, but for software, but I'm
very happy to say that there is
a very strong drive across
multiple different organizations
initiatives at all different
levels of ensuring that software
is of making a first class
citizen research and apply all
those principles in practice and
through policies and listening
to us the couple of the most
relevant ones. It's I want to
particular highlight two
efforts. One is that was done in
the context of our da, through
this pandemic, and the
particular recommendations and
guidelines that came out through
the research software setting
subgroup. And they have a clear
alignment of the four
principles. But mostly, they aim
to give very practical and very
precise instructions on how you
can ensure that research
software can be shared
effectively, and with ideally
minimal effort from the
researchers. And the second
point is that just a few days
ago, the EU publish this sort of
sixth accommodation for
invitation for practice, which
actually did include all those,
both the four principles that I
mentioned before, the best
practices the lecture is working
on and software, release
software guidelines that are
produced by the RBA. I have one
last point to raise so all is
well. So we have about we know
about the principles. We kind of
know more somehow, if we put
really effort on them how to
apply them, hopefully. But if
you look at the individual
level, so what I can do to help
the this is where we go with the
best practices. So in most
cases, as I said, at the
beginning, researchers tend to
develop their own software. And
the reason is that they have
clear knowledge of what we're
trying to do, they are basically
the experts in their domain. And
if you if you would like to have
a max production writing
software software engineer, it's
not easy to find. And even if
you find them, it's not really
affordable, especially for small
groups. So basically 90% of the
people, oh, researchers are
actually self taught in writing
their own software, because this
is what they need to do, which
led to the loss of quality, and
not really good sustainability
of the software itself. So the
best practices and again, an
example here is from elixir,
where I was involved in a sort
of recommending that sense, and
are some really straightforward
ideas that you can apply at all
times to ensure that both your
software aligns fairly well to
the Supreme process were
identified before as well as the
Open Science principle. So
there's the the aim to record
these particular overlap between
fair and assess. So one step at
a time, what can each of us do
to, like aim for that? As I
said, before, assess these are
actually the four principles
make the source code public
available from day one, make the
source the software easy to
find, by offering metadata and
registering to something that
you know, people are knowledge
of, they have knowledge of, and
we can find, always find a
license and adopt one that is
ideally permissive. And always
in line with any third party
dependencies that we have for
your software. And if you want
to build a community around it,
defined how people can actually
help you with the software and
sort of engage with them. A
second point is to utilize
software models plan, which is
something that is emerging. And
in some cases, like in the UK,
they are sort of establishing in
funding schemes, which is mostly
an awareness tool. So how to
ensure that all those aspects
are covered. And you sort of
give some effort in thinking
about them in the first place.
And finally, of course, be part
of the community and sort of be
part of the discussion. And by
just being here. I think you're
sort of doing that already. And
without I really thank you I
hope I've not take too much
time, any questions, I'm more
than happy to address them.