Unknown: My name is Paul Andrea
marthinus, you can find me on
Twitter via my handle or kids
00. This presentation is open to
you by a creative commons CC by
four International. And I've
uploaded to fit chat. So I think
I tick all the boxes that Alex
just mentioned. Great. So from
the western, you just added on
to the MB hack. I hope some of
these are reproducing this
slide. It comes from the World
Bank, it was an analysis they
did with the Open Data handbook
and the World Bank survey. And
they mentioned that open data as
many things for different
people. So it's an opportunity
to share digital resources, make
the community participate and
empower them by giving them
access, giving them transparency
on how the data was collected,
and then share with with
everyone by having no
restrictions and making it
available. So just to expand on
that. I like to give you the
definition of what open data
means by the Open Data
handbook.org. They say that open
data is data that can be freely
used, reuse, and redistributed
by anyone. And on this little
cartoon on the right side, it
says it's an unusually mutation
for you for anyone to use,
modify and enhance your work.
That's the way that we can build
on top of other people's work
and keep improving them. The
concept of open data is actually
nothing new. It comes from the
since internet started this some
guidelines that people should be
following that Tim berners Lee
put together trying to make it a
very simple step by step process
to make your data open as much
as possible. So the first thing
is whatever you want to share,
you can put it online, in would
have four months you have, but
under an open license. So we
Alex just mentioned, there's
different kinds of licenses,
depending if you have code or if
you have text, like in this
case, I'm using Creative Commons
for the license. Then if you
want to go a step farther you go
and make that data available in
a structured way. So for
example, you can put together
all your data collected in a way
that nobody can understand them.
Or you can categorize your data
and put it into different
sections. How is your process
collected? How do you clean your
data and how it's what's the
output of that data. The third
way is making this data once
it's out there, it's on the
internet, you have put it
together kind of in a
spreadsheet, for example, you
can opt to have a nonprofit, or
open format. For example,
instead of having Excel that not
everyone can open, you can have
that as a text file or a comma
separated
file.
So that other people who don't
have access to an Excel
spreadsheet software program,
they can open it with an open
source software program that
exists for other operating
systems. The fourth step is that
you who add a link or URL to the
node, what you're sharing, and
that is the URL. And we would
like to have this euro as a
permanent resource. So something
then it's not going to change
over time. And it's always going
to point to the original data
that you're sharing. Once you
have that you make very good
progress. And the last step that
you can make to contribute to
open data is to link your data.
So it's very unusual that you
have a data that comes by itself
stands alone and links to
nothing. So you have to try to
put some extra information about
how this data links to other
data. If you've collected from
other sources, if you've clean
it from other sources, if you
contributed with other people,
all those things are things that
you can link to your data and
you provide context of what the
result is. So with these steps,
you are helping everyone and
making it possible for others to
reuse your data in a much more
meaningful way. To continue with
this presentation, I'll touch on
this three points. The thing I'm
very important when you share
your data first is ethics. The
second one is how you link your
data a little bit more in
details, and then the fair data
principles. So first, for
ethics. A lot of people think
that the ethics code just at the
end so when you try to
communicate and do distributed
your data, you should be ethical
in what you're sharing. But
instead, I want you to remind
yourself that ethics comes from
the moment that you apply for
funding. Someone is paying for
this research, and they want
this research to be public or
know, what's the motivation for
that? How are you designing your
project? Are you being biased?
Or about your data collection?
How are you resourcing your
data? How is your analysis being
done? Are you influencing the
results of your analysis by any
process that you're taking? How
you interpreting the data? Are
you skipping some steps? Are you
trying to collect what goes in
for a better p value on your
results, all of that it's part
of the data ethics. So remember
that and think that ethics is
all the way in your data product
lifecycle. The other important
thing that I think why the open
data exists, it's to create
knowledge. And to create
knowledge, we have to understand
each other. So for that we use
standards. Also, we use the
syntax. So for example, I've
heard in a presentation about
the human genome where people
were uploading a lot of human
genomes that are not ECG,
correct, but they will some
people will name in hormone,
other people will mimic human,
other people will name a man,
there's so many words that
relate to the same thing. But a
machine will not know this, if
they're not part of vocabulary
or ontology. And to see the
difference, I would recommend
you to go into w three.org. To
see how you can build an
ontology where you can find
ontologies are already existent,
and how you can contribute to
those and name your data in a
reasonable way that has a
relationship that has context
and you provide the connection
to what you're sharing.
Last, but not least, the fair
guiding data principles. This is
also not a new concept. But
there was a published paper in
2016, about thinking all the
things you do as a researcher,
we usually have this little nice
picture of our paper that is two
or three pages long, that we
spend two or three years
collecting and cleaning and
putting together, right. So
there's a lot of work performed,
that it's not visible to the
public. And we want to emphasize
all of that we want to leverage
the work that you're doing, we
want you to have credit for the
work that you're doing. So
that's why the principles were
put together as a guideline. And
it has some steps and
recommendations that I've
mentioned before. And on this
presentation, you have some
links that I recommend you to
follow. So they go further or
explain them in Simple English
terms about what they are. Then
there's the fourth 11, fair data
principles group. If you want to
contribute, you can go there
and, and help. And a new
initiative that I'm also part of
the chain committee is fair for
research software. So initially,
the guiding principles were only
for data. And now we want to
have software for surface
citizen having the same
principles applied to software.
They relate a lot to the data
principles, but there's some
modifications that we need to
do. And you can also read that
paper towards first principles
for research software that was
published last year. Some
communities that are being part
of that I'm still part of that
you can go and look up for more
information on the Open Data
handled by the Open Knowledge
Foundation, the last OSL had a
presentation by one of the
members. There's a lot of
information in the digital
curation center, not only about
open data, but also licensing,
and many other topics. You will
come to have look this the
Forster open science that has a
lot of open materials that you
can reuse. It also has
tutorials, you can share them,
they're all attribution base.
They're open, as before the
Turing way that you might have
heard many times already. Then
there's also the open
conquerable conference that has
set later conferences around the
world. Now everything is online.
So you can also start one of
those in your locality. And for
the TOEFL, the topic of open
data. The research data
Alliance, I think is a very
valuable resource. It's a group
of volunteers around the globe,
that labels the open sharing and
reuse of data. There's so many
different topics out Welcome you
to be part of them. And as Alex
mentioned, if you want to start
using open data, what best to
put hands on into hackathon for
example, there's a lot of
challenges that you can be
solving social, economic, and
environmental, where Open Data
can help. With that, I'd like to
thank you for your attention.
This is also an open image by
patri. HostIn back. And the the
open data is just part of the
road to open science I think all
of you are following in. If you
have questions, you can contact
me by by Twitter.