Unknown: All I'm going to do is
take take a little shift and
just highlight some things that
I have come across that have
been essential in my journey. So
I am supposed to be speaking on
social enterpreneurship. But
that is quite difficult to give
specific tips around how you get
there. But I hope in sharing my
journey that you'll be able to
do something still be relevant
for you. So, my journey started
out in Ghana, I lived there for
17 years, and I highlights the
things I was exposed to because
some people may not necessarily
have this background, I grew up
in a lower middle class family
Christian farming family. And
then I had the opportunity of
spending two years in Costa Rica
to a scholarship, which really
changed my life. And my
perspective, at that age, being
in on a campus with students
from over 60 different countries
is just life altering. After
that went to the US where I did
my undergrad in biology and had
my Master's in computer science.
And at that point, I was very
much interested in
bioinformatics research. And
that was the trajectory in which
I thought I was going, then life
happened, though, because of a
regulation which involved the
visa that I had, I could stay in
the US as long as I wanted. But
all the jobs that I got, I
couldn't take them because now
my employment authorization was
taken away. So it was either
stay in the US and just be
there, or I find something else
to do. And an opportunity opened
up for me to come back home to
Ghana. And I took that I came to
work at a tech incubator where
we're helping startups build
their companies from Nigeria,
Ghana, and Kenya. And that was
an opportunity to also become a
local Open Data advocate, a
leader because a lot of these
companies were not necessarily
thinking about the power of
data, and an open data became
the avenue to really leverage on
these skills. I quickly became
known as the Open Data person.
And that opened opportunities
for me to work on for the next
four years after that, with
first Open Knowledge Foundation,
which is based in the UK working
remotely. supporting other
organizations, journalists,
civil society, organizations,
governments really thinking
about how they can make data
sets open for different
purposes. The experience through
that has allowed me to work
across three different countries
and five continents. And the
power of that, interestingly, is
not in the technical skills,
they are relevant from computer
science and biology. But it has
been the understanding of people
the ability to connect with
people and the problems that
you're solving, and how to kind
of sit with them on whatever
journey they have, and then be
able to work backwards and see
what tools and skills you can
provide to them to enable them
to get to their destination.
Last year, I decided to leave my
job to become a farmer. Yes. And
it is because I think looking at
my career trajectory, my job.
All the jobs I've had, I've
always been pointing to one
thing, how do I help enable
people become better at what
they are good at. And I think
from working all across these
jobs, some of the things that
stood out to me was that in
particularly resource
constraints, environments, you
have very talented people
dealing with very difficult
challenges. And all they need to
have is for people to point out
what specific tools or processes
they can have access to, for
them to get along their journey.
And for me, growing up in a
family farming family, I saw an
opportunity to help smallholder
farmers really leverage on some
of the skills that I have to
really make their lives much
better. So that is what I'm
currently working on. And also
10% of my time is helping other
startups really figure out how
they can leverage on data to
solve problems. So one of the
startups is trying to figure out
how to develop simple tools to
make migrants where kids have
better financial literacy. And
another one is building
educational platforms that can
educate African children. Just
quickly, what is going gold
farms working on we are working
on 14 solving problems, you want
to figure out ways to
consistently produce healthy and
affordable food using
sustainable and accessible
practices.
Then we want to build capacity
of other farms and farmers to do
so sustainability. So transfer
these skills on a broader
distributor level. And then
another challenge that a lot of
smallholder farmers have is that
they usually produce either one
crop depending on on Whether so
can we think of ways to
diversify that, but also move
their raw materials to process
forms. And then finally, make
farms spaces of attraction,
innovation, recreation and fun.
They are very technical problems
that we need to solve all of us
this, which will leverage on
computation economics,
anthropology. And I think that's
what makes it exciting as a
social intrapreneur. If I can
call myself that now. On a
typical day, I am reading about
and implementing research to
these problems that are listed
out. So reading papers around
geolocation, and how can you
figure out that constraint of
soil in order to determine what
crops can grow around that
without having access to
internet. So these are very
interesting problems to be
really thinking through. I think
the most powerful thing putting
together an enable the team of
people, you can solve this
alone. So how do you sell that
vision to people and allow that
team to have the capacity to
really solve the problem with
and then believing in ourselves,
it's, you get two points where
nobody else believes me by
believing yourself as a team,
they keep on working at it, and
you get encouraged and you keep
on going. Because at the core,
you believe that you're solving
something, at least for solving
and other people. I'm just gonna
quickly go through some what I
call carrier anecdotes, these
are just my own reasons. be
versatile, that's one thing I've
learned. One of the things that
have been important for me is to
initially generalize, be able to
have some understanding of a
broad set of different things.
So if you're a research person
still understand how to
communicate with people still
understand how to facilitate how
to even do comedy, if you want
justice, be versatile, at the
same time to have one thing that
you are known for, for me, is
the ability to take complex
things and simplified for other
people to have and to be able to
use. See people and lets people
see, and what do I mean by that?
It is so easy to get bogged down
and technical things and
research and Miss people or
focus on the job, those are all
relevant. But I think when you
see people in all the jobs I've
done, I've had at least one
person that I still stay in
touch with, who knew me for more
than what I was able to do as
part of my role. So they could
either come talk to me, bounce
ideas off me knew about my
passions outside of work. And
even if you find employers that
will be clear about that, that
is actually much more powerful.
And also let people see you,
especially people who are from
backgrounds that are not
necessarily predominance in
whatever space that you're
working in. Make sure that you
create opportunities for
yourself to be seen speak. And I
know sometimes it can be
difficult, but speak,
participate in events, try as
much as possible for people to
also know that you are more than
just your title. And this is
kind of like a joke, candy
identity, no job, no, do not do
that do not ground the identity
in your job, your job will go
away, it will disappear. Lets
your identity be much more than
that. So that when your job
changes, when you want to do
something else, you still have
that identity that will keep you
going when things fail, you
still have that identity now
keep going. And that's what's
been keeping me going. And I
think in the same sense, people
have seen my passions and when
even I was leaving my job last
year, they were encouraging me.
My team was saying go do it.
We'll support you in that. The
last thing I'll say brief, most
important thing in this life is
your life. Everything else is
replaceable. And with that, I'll
say stay human or humane and be
open to to whatever is possible
given the stuff that you have.
So I'll stop here.