Unknown: Huge welcome. And we're
excited to be working with you.
So what we focus on is helping
early stage researchers,
potential academic leaders, and
really anyone who has an
interest in open science
practice. So you don't have to
be an early stage career, if you
wants to still go through the
program, that's fine as well.
And one of our focuses is to
make sure that you become an
ambassador for open science. So
whilst we we have everyone
applying with a specific
project, so that you may be
working on, we hope that this
will actually apply to all
aspects of the science and the
research that you're working on.
And that hopefully, this will be
something you can also pass on
to others in the future. And
again, we can only really
advance where we're actually
working with with with other
people rather than against other
people and building on each
other's successes. But one of
the problems is that people are
often afraid of actually
sharing, we try and break down
as many barriers here as we can,
as well as some of the fears
that may or may not actually be
things that people tend to
encounter all that often. So
some some of these fears might
be being criticized or being
scoped. But we like to talk
about working openly without
feeling vulnerable, and without
worry about having to worry so
much about something about these
types of things. So we will be
working one step at a time to go
through some of these steps. So
you may have already looked at
the open life science syllabus,
in fact, if you've applied,
there's a very good chance
you've spent quite a long time
looking at this. But because we
have this over a whole 16 weeks
sort of means that we touch on a
few concepts, and then you have
a week or two to actually apply
it to your project. And then we
touch on more concepts. And this
means that rather than this
being a concentrated, you know,
one week program or something,
it means that you have a lot of
time to reflect and reapply and
work on things in between all of
the cohort calls. And then
there's also your mentors who
will speak with you on every
other week to actually chat
about how this is going and
reflect and figure out and act
as an external viewpoint. And
so, the cohort covers the cohort
based training. So sweet things
like today, today is largely an
intro, but we will go into a lot
more specific subjects over the
next 16 weeks, we also have the
one on one mentoring. And then
the hands on practice is really
up to us project lead. So this
is the part where you apply what
we've been learning to your
projects. And one thing that you
will see us talking about a lot
is the Mozilla open leadership
framework. So the open life
science was born as a child of
the Mozilla open leaders, that
doesn't run anymore, actually.
But they've left a lot of
amazing materials. You'll see
occasionally you may see Mozilla
and some of our slides or on
some of the handouts that we
provide. Because they launched a
bunch of different amazing open
leadership style programs. This
one specifically focuses on open
science. But this has also been
applied to AI and to hardware,
and to many, many other
different areas, that people are
actually applying the open
leadership framework and
basically as a way of
structuring building community,
and building collaboration and
pathways into the projects that
you're working on. And this is a
phrase that you will also see a
lot of the time, and we often
bold, different parts of it
depending on what we're actually
talking about. So I'll read it
out, open it as design, build
and empower their projects and
communities for understanding
sharing and participation and
inclusion. So depending on the
lesson that we may be teaching
in any given week, we may be
talking about the empowering, or
they'll be talking about the
designing or some other parts.
So you'll see this repeated a
lot but with a different
emphasis each time as we go
through. And this is part of the
Mozilla open leadership
framework. So this is again, a
slide you may see a lot, we will
highlight different boxes within
this or different bullet points
within this as we go along. But
it just sort of gives you an
idea of some of the focuses that
we look into. So we look at
participation and inclusion and
different ways that we can build
that into the program and
empower people. We look at ways
that we can build sharing into
the program. And we also look at
ways that we can design so that
people understand what's going
on effectively. And so some of
the different roles of open
science communities are some of
the different things that we
will touch upon over the next
few weeks will include sharing
your data. We will talk about
sharing your source code if you
have source code, so we're not
expecting everyone to do so. But
some of you may do so. Equally,
we talk about about sharing
hardware, but again, it's fine
if you don't have hardware,
these are just some of the
different things that you may
encounter. And it's also good to
be aware of as well.
Now we talk about dissemination
such as sharing up papers and
protocols, the more traditional
ways that that can be open
access, or if you're sharing
your results early. That's pre
printing. I think that's
actually been highlighted a lot
recently with COVID, perhaps
preprints have become a lot more
common and in the spotlight than
they used to be. We talked about
sharing with us your papers,
sharing training, such as open
education, and also
collaborating openly with a
public. Citizen Science may not
always be pinpointed as a method
of open science. But it
definitely does involve a lot of
openness. And also just
generally networking and
connecting with others in your
fields. And so these are a few
of the things that we cover,
it's definitely not the only
things we cover. That's one of
the things to look forward to
over the next few weeks, we'll
also invite a lot of guest
speakers to speak on these
specific topics. One of the most
important premises of open life
science is that openness should
be built in by design to what
you're doing rather than by
accident, or by a default. And
to explain why that is. So this
is a very sort of tech oriented
explanation. But looking at 160
tech companies. This study
actually found that the level of
strategic intent and openness
tended to correlate with market
performance, or to make that
slightly less techie sounding.
Basically, when you
intentionally design the ways
that people interact with you,
and the ways that people join
your community, and the ways
that people continue to
participate in your community,
it tends to be a lot more
effective, then if you simply
put something online and say,
Please come. So we try and focus
on building these effective
useful, inclusive communities
that actually are designed to
have people participating and
enjoying that participation. But
yeah, design openness and your
work and don't let it be a
thoughtless default.
So
chief positive culture change,
yes. Okay. Right. So one thing
that we're looking at also is
allowing you to achieve the
positive culture change within
your community. So we don't want
to just accept the status quo
and some places that may be
things aren't open or in other
places that the opening open
communities aren't necessarily
inclusive or empowering. So we
like to encourage that
we share a leadership we share a
vision and we push towards the
things that are actually
meaningful. And I think that's
everything for the intro.