Unknown: First of all, thank you
open lifecyle for inviting me to
share what we do I consider our
work is super complimentary. And
I'm really impressed with the
results of the program about
myself. I'm Julio diancie. I'm
from monocytes Cantina. I'm
currently living in Switzerland.
I'm finishing my PhD and open
science hardware and its
contribution to democratizing
knowledge production in the
global south. And as most people
in open science, I have many
hats. So I'm also co organizing
the Latin American community of
open science hardware. And I
have co founded with Alex
kucera, and an underlying asset
program that is a sibling of
open lifesite. It's called Open
hardware makers, where we give
support to new open hardware
projects. So but what is open
science hardware? What is it all
about? Okay, so it basically
boils down to this month, people
who want to make sales, need
tools to make science. And
nowadays, those tools are what
we call a black box. And they
are a bad box, because we just
input samples for information or
some kind of input, and we get
an output out of them. But we're
not 100% sure of the processes
that produce this outputs. Of
course, we know about the
principles, but we cannot
inspect tools. And the fact that
we cannot do so brings many
problems to researchers in
general. First of all, this, as
we don't know how they work,
these tools are really difficult
to modify and customize. And I
don't know if you aren't aware,
but scientists are having
studies to be one of the groups
that customize their tools the
most, which makes sense, right,
because you're always trying to
pursue new questions and to see
a bit more, so you need your
tools to be able to change with
your ideas. Second, being
proprietary, these are hard to
maintain. So we have personal
example, unfortunately, with a
corporate crisis in the US where
some hospitals, they don't want
to repair ventilators afraid of
breaking pain and loss. Another
example Another problem with
this is that science tools are
usually produced by a small
number of companies, and this
are therefore able to sell in
general, very expensive prices.
So many universities around the
world cannot access to
equipment. So as you can see,
these are consequences that
consequences that are faced by
almost everyone in academia. But
the impact is certainly bigger
in those countries that have low
investment in science and
technology on one side, because
science tools are more expensive
in the global south. But also
when science equipment breaks
down. Let's say in the UK, it's
a very different experience as
what it does in Ecuador come in
owner container. So why because
you depend on the supplier who
charges you a lot for sending a
specialist professionals or
replacement parts. This
generates huge delays in the
case that it's possible. And you
also have the restriction of
imports and exports, which makes
it very difficult to access. So
all this very practical stuff
translates into questions that
are not pursued translates into
limitations for for research and
less powerful, he says, at the
end of the day, less diversity
of perspectives and science. And
the main idea, or the main
takeaway here is that we are
reinforcing the pattern where
most science is produced by
those who have already money to
produce it. So some people
started thinking about why not
opening the designs of science
stores and some changes and
access to hardware design during
the lesson years makes us think
that it's possible. So for
example, the reliability of
software free open source
software for designing and
testing hardware. The rise of 3d
printing is ideal for
prototyping and for low volume
distributed production. The
access to cheaper electronic
components and projects like
Arduino the democratized
electronic design, the
massification of the internet as
a way to share experiences and
learn from each other. And the
work of an amazing community
that's been doing a lot for
improving the ways in which
hardware design is ensured.
The good thing is that it's been
a while and the results are
showing. So here I'm just I will
just show three very good
examples of open science how to
work in action. But there are
many, many others inside and
outside academia. And the good
thing is that because they're
open, they can learn from each
other. So on the left in
Tanzania open flexure is a
project that has enabled short
circuit production of
microscopes that are being used
in education, research and
clinical diagnosis of malaria.
Open flexor is a UK project
originally, but they are
producing now microscopes at a
local makerspace and this can be
easily The source repaired
without dealing with inputs and
huge costs and delays. Another
example or your mouth is success
in conservation biology, you can
imagine it as a very big ear
that logs sound all around. It
has a very big community of
users improving and customizing
it. And it's leading to
developing new methods to
address research questions that
before were consider untestable.
Finally, here, in in bedroom,
epidemiology, researchers have
designed and built an open
source device to track malaria
spread in Amazonian indigenous
populations, and they were able
to do so in a way that respects
the preferences of these
populations. And that tolerates
also the very difficult
conditions weather conditions of
the Amazon. It's so it's it's
such a growth in open science
hardware that we also see, for
example, policies, national
policies, policy recommendations
for Finland, which are
suggesting the country to adopt
an open science hardware
strategy at a national level. So
that was these year 2020. So
just to sum up, open science
hardware is any piece of
hardware that is used for
scientific investigations, and
that anyone can obtain assemble
your study, modify, share, and
sell because you can build of
course hardware, but you may
also want to just buy it and
make sure that you can modify it
or do anything you want with it
later. The word hardware in some
languages may bias us towards
electronics. But open hardware
open science, however, refers
also besides standard lab
equipment, to auxiliary
materials, sensors, biological
research, regions, analog
musical, digital electronics,
and also mechanical tools. And
this huge circle in the middle
reminds us that the heart of
open science hardware is good
documentation. So user guides,
but also contribution
contribution guides, sharing
files in editable formats, many
other good practices that the
community has defined to ensure
that everyone has access to your
hardware design, with the idea
of improving projects instead of
constantly reinventing the
wheel. So one of the main ideas
here for the committee from the
community is that if we really
want open science to be
transformative, we cannot limit
Open Science practice to open
data and open access
publications. That's a minimum
threshold. But if we really want
to open science to other actors
inside and outside academia, we
need to be able to share the
tools we use to work. And this,
as I mentioned, has benefits in
terms of efficiency and of
course, reproducibility in
science, but also in opening who
is able to read your scientific
knowledge and whose questions
matter. So there you see the
logo in the bottom got community
is the community gathering
people pushing for Open Science
hardware to be ubiquitous by
2025? And it really might do to
check the manifesto assign it if
you agree with our values.
Finally, how can you get
involved? How can you
participate? Okay, so the entry
point I would say this, the gosh
forum, you see that you are out
there, you can drop a question,
people are super friendly, you
can search for the regional
communities in the forum and
connect to the people that are
near you. You can also use the
open no help project, which was
fine, the ability protocol that
was established for open
hardware in general, not only
for science, because you will
see they're open Hello projects
and in many different platforms.
Some of them are in GitHub, get
lab, wiki, factory,
Instructables, hackaday. There
are many platforms, but open
know how is a protocol that
unifies findability, whatever
platform your project is in. You
can search for keywords there.
You can also read or submitted
assigned to the journal open
Howard the cool stuff is that
your documentation will also be
peer reviewed, which is super
interesting. And you can follow
open homemakers in Twitter,
where we will announce our next
cohort after this year where we
run a super big community and
expert consultation to improve
our curriculum and program. So
that's all thank you so much for
listening. Those are the ways
you can contact me and feel free
to ask me any questions. Thank
you.
Oops. That was holy. Holy is on
the slack. So you can ask
questions there. We have also
left.
Sorry.
Yes, tiny glitch there. So that
was 844. Today, before we close
out, we want you to know that we
also have homework for today.
Let me find the pack MD Just so
you know the homework frequency
is reducing now, what you have
done in the past, which which
was about creating README file,
starting your contribution file,
starting your code of conduct,
and roadmapping, these are
something that you will continue
to advance. So it's not that the
week have weeks are over, you
are going to work on this. So
please continue working on those
aspects. In the next week,
please start to share your
Project Online. We have
demonstrated good pages, you can
also use Google site, which
could be similar for a lot of
people who don't want to use
GitHub. We also can use
WordPress free or other any
platform. If you want to just
strictly be on GitHub, that's
also fine. But please, have a
detailed README, please choose a
license, start working on your
code of conduct, create a
project development plan, we
have created a small assignment
that can help you use a dial
method. The that is linked in
the line number 466. And after
these assignment, think about
putting your roadmap up. But
this is something that we will
also talk about in next week,
mostly because we will talk
about science dissemination. So
our project is not just about
developing but sharing as well.
So this is something we want to
start working on in the next
week onwards. Without we're done
on time. That's amazing. Any
questions that you have, we can
take it in the last one minute
but I'll stop recording. Thank
you for joining today.
Thanks, Slavica.