Unknown: We'll be talking about
the release. But first, I will
introduce myself. My name is
Natasha Kozak and a community
manager at the Netherlands
Science Center. My background is
life sciences, cell biophysics,
and bioinformatics. And for a
while I've been research
software engineer. So I've been
developing research software,
and for the world for a while
now, I'm the community manager
in the area of research,
software engineering. So I
usually help research software
engineers connect to their
communities and help them help
them with their projects. And I
guess that's why I'm talking
about the readme files, because
that's part of the things how do
you interact? Or make the
interaction better with the
community that is interested in
your software? Or how do you
make or get your community
interested in your projects. And
so from this very short talk,
we'll learn how to use the
readme to communicate
information of your project
effectively, how to write clear
description of the project,
which is very important, and
it's actually quite difficult.
Despite the wording, I think
it's easy to not realize that
we're using jargon, or we're
making things more complicated
because of our background. And
that we know much more than
other people. And I do. And
we'll show some examples are
good examples of README files.
And I guess your assignment will
be to either revise or improve
or start your README file for
your project. And so again, we
have this matrix of, of how,
where things are in the or less
project. So this is part of
build for understanding, it's
about communicating things about
your project. It's about
facilitation, collaboration is
about facilitation, maintenance,
and helping with the project
management. And so the readme is
like a dorm app for your
project. It's the first thing
that people will see when they
go to GitHub, they go to your
GitHub page of the project.
That's what they see the the
content of the of the readme
file. So this is like your
unique opportunity to get to
make a good impression. It's
like the the first impression
when you make when you met meet
someone first time. So this is
when your potential contributors
or users are going to eat your
project. And that's why it's
very important that they don't
get discouraged when they see
it, but they actually get
interested. So how can we make
it happen? And but first, what
actually is the readme. And the
reason is, it's a text file,
usually. And it's, it's found in
the root directory of your
repository. So and all of you
are working now on GitHub, with
your projects. And when you
create a project, GitHub will
automatically create a readme
file for you based on the
information that you provided
when you created the project. So
there will be a header which
will be a name of your project.
And then there will be a short
description, the description of
the put in when you created the
project. So I guess you already
started with a readme file, it's
usually all in caps. So all in
caps README, it could be written
in dot txt, or readme.mark.md,
which stands for markdown and
markdown files are automatically
rendered on GitHub in a nice
way. And they give you more
possibility to, to add some
design things in your README
over the text files, simple text
files. Yeah, and as I already
said, this is the first thing
that people will see. And so
what's in the readme? If there
should be a description of what
is your project about why is it
important, and who is the
audience of the project, and
wonder mode, what makes your
project special or exciting,
like why people would should get
excited about it, and how they
can get started either to use it
or collaborate with you or to
contribute to the project. And
where they can find the key
resources to like start the
journey with your project.
And you can use the open canvas
to start your README file. And I
will show some examples and
examples of the things that you
can add to make your reading
more effective. This is the
example from the several models
up and you see here. There is
the in in large letters there is
the name of the project. And
then there is the vision of the
project we already like it's
like the first thing you see is
the name and the vision of the
project. So it gives you the
already the perspective what
what is this about? And then
there's there's this very
welcoming message. And there are
some links to more resources to
find out to learn more about the
project. And usually also have,
so the name, the vision, the the
welcome message, project
description, these are all the
things that we need in the
readme file, you can also add
information how to contribute
how to get involved. In the
principle we already had, it's a
good place to put information
about the license that is used
apart from having a license
file, and also information about
the code of conduct and how to
report violations, because you
want people who join to know
that there is a code of conduct,
and that this is the Safe, safe
place to interact with others.
And what else communicate the
expectations around the
readiness? It is important, not
every project is ready from the
start. But you want to make sure
that you communicated clearly
what is the status of the
project? And is it very early
stage? Or is it ready for use?
and communicate expectations for
managing contributions? Like
what kind of contributions are
looking for? And are you like,
what is the level of your time
commitment? How much can you
support the contributors to your
project, because maybe you don't
have the resources and you can't
spend all you have limited
resources, or you have like
specific ways that you would
like to collaborate with others.
And that also means describe
communication channels. And
here's the example from their
retro hack GitHub repository. So
this is the hackathon, which is
focused on trying to represent
research papers. And you see
here, first of all, there is
this welcoming message. But also
you see the repo status, which
is in this case, it's Wi Fi,
which is working progress so the
emphasises it's it's still
working progress. But it also
shows you how you can join the
conversations by joining slack
by pressing the button join
slack join us. And you can also
keep in touch and see what's
happening by subscribing to the
newsletter. And you might be
already familiar with, with
badges. So GitHub uses those
badges on README files. These
are very nice way with a
colorful way of communicating
various things that are about
your project, there's a version
of your software, if you have
releases, the license, the
quality of the code, the
documentation, testing, doesn't
have a continuous integration,
things like that. And then yeah,
you can sprinkle it with emojis
to be more colorful. Not
everyone likes it. But if you if
you like it, that's also you can
make it I think it makes it a
bit more friendly. And sometimes
you need to communicate
something which is more
complicated. You want to show
how to do something, you could
use animated GIF for that. And
as I was mentioned, is it's very
easy to overcomplicate things in
the readme file or make it
difficult for others to
understand what the project is
about because you have an expert
dancesport you know already much
more about it. And and so, this
is, so how can we make it
easier? How can we make sure
that it's easier and accessible
for others? And you might have
heard about Randall Munroe is
the person who draws XKCD comics
or write sex they're both writes
and rich and Joe's and he wrote
this book things explainer when
he
basically like a challenge how
to describe complicated stuff in
the word in simple words, so he
used 10 100 most common words in
English language. And he
described different things like
in this case, it's abhor five,
because the rocket is not one of
the 10 100 most popular words,
and and then there are tools
that actually can help you do
it. You can use the there's the
link here to the upgrade or
five, you can use the editor
that will help you to write your
README file using only those
10 100 most popular words. And
and then there's the other
editor that will help you also
with with accessible read me
it's Hemingway up. Yep, I think
that's it. I don't know if
you're young, you're planning
the exercise in breakouts with
the readme files, so that's
adequate. Okay. Yeah. So that's,
that's it for me. And please put
in if there are more resources
So if you want to look up some
examples of README files that
are here, and put in the
hackathon, the ideas, your ideas
for good README file, if you
know something, if I didn't
mention, it's a lot of things
that I haven't mentioned. So if
you have, if you've seen some
great reading files, you can put
examples, they're an IDS. And
that's it for me. Thank you.