Unknown: All right, so we are
still in the open by design.
What we want to do is to
discover how to use a roadmap to
plan our work and find
contribution for our open
project. And we're going to also
look at few examples, as we saw
for open canvas. So open leader
design, and now we're gonna move
to a bit about empowering others
to collaborate within the open
communities. And when we think
about empowering others, it's a
lot about knowledge sharing.
Keeping with this framework, we
are at this part, we're still
designing for participation and
inclusion, we want to think
about what the project's
identity is, and what are ways
people interact with my project.
The intention behind this is to
create an a welcoming space,
make a good impression, so
others know that they are in the
right place, and you know, that
you're communicating well
explain how one can get involved
in your project, and let them
know what's happening next. So
they can decide if this is the
right project for them to be
involved in. What goes into the
roadmap, there are three things
that you will be thinking about
the would go into roadmap. First
is project summary, and you
actually creating this welcoming
space, telling people how to get
involved. And what is the
timeline timeline may be
changing quite a lot, but it is
still a good idea to tell them
what you are at what would you
be doing next. So this project
summary in welcoming space would
require would be required. So
people who are visiting your
project can get oriented with
where your project has
information, what kind of
resources do you have, it is
important for them to understand
where they are often in a new
project, the biggest blocker is
that the newness of that space,
and you want to help them to
feel familiar with the space
that they are in having the
project summary as the first
page. So if you all are familiar
with GitHub, you wouldn't be
calling it as a readme. But if
you are familiar with any other
product, you would always see a
summary page, which gives an
overview of the project, it
helps to give a clear focus on
when writing the rest of the
roadmap. Second is how to get
involved This is about your
contributors. It's possible that
some contributors are available
to jump in right away. But they
can do that only if they know
what is the task in hand. And if
the skills that they have is
actually appropriate for your
project. Some people might not
be available right now, but they
know about your project and want
to come back. And they should
also know how they can get
involved when they're coming
back. So you need to have a
documentation that you wish they
would be able to check out. This
is the start of your roadmap,
the timeline, it organizes tasks
to complete your project around
milestones. This is, again,
we're going to come back to all
these concepts in the future
calls for these are for you to
think about already. How do you
see your project in the next
weeks or so? How do you see your
project at the end of wellness?
Or how do you see it afterwards.
So you need to think about
milestone, these are significant
turning points or events that
will move the project forward.
So this is also allowing you to
assess what the progress of your
project has been. You can have a
status goal, for example, a
feature release or minimum
viable product. You can also be
hosting an event for example,
giving a talk or attending a
hackathon or hosting a community
call. You can have timeframe as
well, you can define your
milestone in three levels, you
can have a short term, you can
have a medium term and a long
term goal. Therefore, anyone
who's available right now can
get involved in short term
people who want to come back
they would be looking at medium
and long term milestones. Then
just telling the milestones is
not enough, you are the project
lead and therefore you need to
define what kind of direction
you want to take. And these
direction can be clarified by
listing out the tasks that these
milestone will involve.
You can and these are iterative
process again, right this is
this is not something that we're
expecting you to complete right
away. But this is the process
you want to implement in your
project. So you would want to
list tasks by stating what needs
to be done, what is the success
looks like and the success in
terms of what would complete the
project milestone one single
milestone, you don't need to
think about the full project at
the moment. You also want to
share pointers to get started
and these pointers could be
skill building resources, or it
could be about contribution
guideline. It could be anything
that can help you contributor to
feel that they are in a position
to get involved. And you also
need to state why this task is
important and reinforce your
vision. And this is very useful
because these contributors are
there to support your project
not work for you. So you don't
need to look at them as someone
who will complete a task, but
they you want to involve them in
building a project and make them
feel as part of your journey. So
how to share the roadmap, we you
can have a file called
roadmap.md, which is markdown,
but you can start as well, with
a simple document, which can be
the first page of your project,
if you are thinking of building
a website, in the GitHub, it
could be a readme file, you
could also create issues. And
these issue can have labels, for
example, you can look at these
two examples. Again, as I said,
you're going to come back to
these slides, you will go
through it slowly, one by one,
and you will be able to look at
these examples. So I'm going to
open one example. Because we
have some time. So this is a
roadmap that Open Knowledge maps
on open discovery have written,
this is their road. This is what
it looks like they have a
motivation of what this project
is about. They give an
introduction to Open Knowledge
maps, and they list out all the
resources that they have
developed, what kind of services
they have, what kind of
infrastructure they have, what
kind of community engagement
plan they have, what openness
means to them, what do they
think their sustainability of
the project would be like? And
what is the governance, so this
is a lot of them might be quite
high level for a new project.
But if your project has existed
for a while, you might want to
also think about a product
detail. And then you have work
plan. And let's look at the work
plan. And the work plan. They
have clearly clearly written
what what are the main three
pillars for them are, they
explain each of them for each of
them, they actually provide what
kind of infrastructure that they
are using. And they have gone
into as much detail as it is
required for them to ensure that
their contributors know about
their project. So that this
might be quite detailed. Over
the next few weeks. We will also
share some examples with you in
the slack or in the notes. So
please have a look at all those
and I'm sure you might have your
own ideal project in mind. It's
a good chance for you to go back
to those projects and look at
how they're doing it and why
they're doing it that way. Okay,
so with that, I'll say that we
can finish this part