Unknown: My name is Natasha, I'm
currently working for higher
expiry sciences. It is a startup
that came from the University of
the Western Cape. Hi, Peter. And
and we were originally working
on HIV research. And what
happened was that it was during
the time that the government's
encouraged people to peyten
before publishing, so they
wanted to generate some some
revenue from the publicly funded
money going into university. So
we were in a very fortunate
position, for many reasons, we
were a very tight knit group
working together. And it wasn't
the right time at the right
place at the right time to do
HIV research. Similar to people
doing viral research at the
moment during this year. So
instead of walking you through
my specific career path, because
after my PhD, I went into law
for a year and I also worked in
industry at Roche for a year
before going back and doing a
postdoc. And what I wanted to do
given this interesting and quite
strange idea was to look at
everything that is similar. So
the things that are universal to
to my career path. And I kind of
like thinking about it, as this
infinity or the circle. So it
doesn't matter how much you
diverged, you kind of come back
to the same points again. And
I've found this very useful this
year to look back and think
about the things that have been
universal in life. And if I'm
still moving towards that goal
in the career, so it doesn't
matter what career moves, you
make it whether you still
working in towards this, this
the same direction. So for me,
these things are curiosity. So
throughout, whether it's an
academia or startup, I'm very
intrinsically driven by
curiosity. And this is often the
question and then, so what comes
next. So this has been
universal, whether that's
instead of startup or in
academia, the second thing is
learning and learning a slightly
different curiosity, because in
the startup, specifically, they
can be learning in things as
wide as company structuring in
terms of hiring new people,
which is somewhat similar to
academia, where you are managing
people. And so so learning for
me is specifically also during
the times when you feel like
you're not gaining knowledge,
necessarily doing the same thing
every day. If you look very
clearly, you are always learning
and if you define it for
yourself, then you will feel
that you're moving forward in
whatever you're doing. And then
the next thing is collaboration.
And this is something that
malvika touched on. And it's
something that's that that I
really enjoy, and whether that's
an academia trying to work with
different research groups, or
within the startups
specifically, where we're such a
close knit team, and we work
together on a daily basis, and
we want to share our work and
build a successful company. So
collaboration is a really strong
one. And these are the things
that are similar to between
academia, and and and startups.
And then the last one is a
positive impact. And with a
positive impact, and this can be
from teaching. So when you see
students have it that that aha
moments,
up to users of software of your
software, where they can now
produce a result for a drug
resistance results for patients
that they couldn't do before. So
So and also. So these things are
the things that I've found that
are very similar between
academia and the startup, and
where people often try and find
the differences and try and say
that one is better than the
other. Like I've preferred
looking back and going and
looking at the things that are
universal for me and, and
defining data paths that I've
been following. And I hope that
I can keep doing that moving
forward. And I it's always
interesting to to provide career
guidance when I still feel like
I'm on a journey myself. But
based on that, and this image is
a little bit more issue like so
even though I've spoken about
the spiral and that you keep
getting back to the same kind of
universal theme. It's also
you're allowed to acknowledge
that you can change themes and
you can jump between these
staircases from time to time.
And, and for me, I have recently
moved to with with the COVID
pandemic, our company has gone
completely distributed and
therefore I have moved to
Amsterdam. So things have
changed. To me quite a bit, but
in terms of moving to a new
country, those themes remain the
same the curiosity, the learning
about new cultures, and, you
know, collaborating and making
new connections and then having
a positive impact in everything
that I do.