Unknown: Hi everyone, again,
thank you for the invitation.
urban life science team. I am
very happy to be part of the
folks who bring some expertise
to the second urban life science
cohort. I will talk briefly
about urban education and
training today, most of my time
would go into presenting metal
sensors case study. Please bear
with me until slide five, if
you're wondering what that name
means. So I am Laura Seon, mid
career researcher from an
currently ad when Osiris
Argentina. However, what brought
me here today is my role as one
of my data associates, co
founders. These are metal
Celsius, and my theater handle,
in case you want to tweet about
this presentation, and thank
you, Sharon mccutchen for
sharing this beautiful picture
on unsplash so I could reuse it.
Building on a great presentation
by color give it for the first
cohort in iOS. I will start by
giving a definition of urban
education according to open
education, global urban
education and compasses,
resources, tools and practices
that employ a framework of open
sharing to improve educational
access and effectiveness
worldwide. Still, building on
gallops presentation here, Open
Educational Resources must
follow the fair principal. This
means that resources should be
final accessible already. So
yeah, I'm missing their
interoperational here, that's
more for data. This the last bit
of reusable is key because
uploading your educational
resources to a public website
does not make them very usable
really. So open educational
resources require license
allowing reuse makes sharing.
And this is a slide five so here
it goes. The finishing of that
term metal associate our case
study today checks all the boxes
I'm I just mentioned in the last
slide in particular all the
resources developed by metal
associate are sharing. I shared
our shared to sorry, using a CC
BY 4.0 license. So the name
Madison says meaning Madison see
it can be translated from
Spanish to English as
meditating. Medicine Xia is an
initiative that teaches to teach
in Spanish last March with the
need to switch every class from
a person to online in Argentina,
where we don't know when in
person classes we ever assume
yet. This friends with whom we
have been working in the art
community and I co founded
Metallo sensia. Our mission is
to nurture a community of
Spanish speaking educators by
teaching concrete, evidence
based and student centered
educational methods. We
collaboratively develop open re
usable and accessible resources
to foster effective training
practices. We are heavily
inspired by the carpentries and
open education organization
worth checking out if you're not
familiar with it yet. I bet a
lot of you know about it here.
So you might be wondering why
there is a need for metal sensia
when there are so many open
educational resources about
teaching already available?
Well, on the one hand, most
state of the art resources and
communities around them are
majorly in English or our
English speaking communities. On
the other hand, English is an
enormous barrier in Latin
America. translations of
contents are not enough for
culturally responsible teaching,
meaning our learners where they
are in Latin America means to
not make assumptions about the
knowledge of technologies such
as zoom, slack or Google Docs,
and being conscious about
Internet access and
accessibility differences. There
is a ton of the ran leveling
work needed before meaningful
international integration is
feasible. Communities of
Practice are still a new concept
in our region. In mid March, the
need for all we have learned
from several international
communities of practice was more
evident than ever. We had the
knowledge, the experience and
the moral obligation to share it
ASAP.
So seven months later, our core
team of carpentries or our
studio certified trainers and
instructors added Nikolas
another carpentries trainer and
instructor. Our collaborators
teams, the team now includes 10
collaborators in three countries
and six different cities in
Argentina. They are our suite of
certified instructors carpentry
structures are not originally
knowledgeable, accessibility
experts. We are also blessed by
an international advisory team
that it's guiding us. We are not
only pictures in our website or
interact only through slack. We
also have periodic team
meetings. This is a picture of
part of our team during our last
monthly meeting, only eight of
us were able to join. Although
missing key folks, this is how
it looks to work together for
us. While talking while taking
this picture, we realize that
this is how it will always look
for us because Metro senses team
is geographically spread. And
our budget will not go into
meeting in person anytime soon.
meeting in person is not
currently a priority,
particularly because we know how
to function very well online.
This is great news not only for
medicine, but also for our
planet. among various
activities. We have our three
hour hands on workshop
introduction to teaching align
our 30 times, we completed a
carpenter's instructor training
for 19 participants at my home
are now instructors certified by
the carpentry. We are piloting a
two hour hands on workshop, and
how to use zoom to teach online.
This is the most common request
from our participants. Also a
three hour workshop for creating
interactive tutorials to teach
to code with art using the art
package learner will reach more
than 1200 500 Spanish speaking
teachers across 19 countries, we
have reached educators from all
over Argentina including
underserved rural areas. Our
learners teach mostly exactly
natural sciences, but also other
disciplines. We foster a
community through a 100% Spanish
speaking slack workspace where
we apologize when we share
materials in English. It
includes more than 300 members.
We are also active tweets and an
N a synchronous content creators
these 19 past include
contributions from persons who
are part of our community. We
also will community by working
together with other communities
and institutions at local,
regional and international
levels. Our current materials
have been repurposed to suit
audiences of early career
researchers at the national
record agricultural technology
Institute in Argentina. We
taught tutorials for Latino and
Latin American conference for
the use of art in research and
development. We also repurpose
our materials to encourage the
Spanish speaking our latest
community war while to continue
having events gatherings and
teaching online through pandemic
times. Finally, we hosted a
genuine generously carpentries
authorize Allah carta is a la
carte instructor training
worship in Spanish that had a
95% checkout rate. More links to
other communities include
Nadella and Argentine event and
community that shares our
principles and values and
sources are supported supporter
for the event this year. We also
learned metal sensor
infrastructure to cause the
launching of pilotis alto in
Bolivia. And for presentation of
several are related initiatives
from Latin America at use our
2020 and an international
diversity and inclusion panel
also at use our 2020. So in the
upcoming month, we keep thinking
globally while acting locally
considering the different
realities of Latin American
Spanish speaking educators.
However, one lesson we learned
is that metal sensor will not be
sustainable only on volunteer
time that we are actively
looking for funding and to
become fiscally sponsored. We
also plan to give developing
workshops to teach how to teach
programming bifen are good and
other open source and open data
science methods. We also plan to
measure our impact and publish
our experience openly.
All of our activities were
possible thanks to our team's
volunteer time and 1000 US
dollar grant from the open
bioinformatics foundation that
supports our words zoom Kala Lee
and other infrastructure. And in
this link, you can find more
information about Metallo
sensia. This is our English
version. So no worry, no Spanish
in that one that the rest of his
Spanish but we also have an
English version. So thank you
for your attention.