Unknown: I'm an experimental
psychologist by training. I've
been at the University of
Manchester for 17 years now. And
this was actually after I spent
both three years working in
industry and doing a couple of
postdocs. So I've kind of, you
know, shifted around a little
bit over the last few years. And
I think talking about academia
today, and this, you know, brief
overview of my view of academia
today is pretty quite different
from what my view would have
been just just, you know, three
or four years or so ago. I'm
currently Senior Lecturer in the
Division of neuroscience, and
experimental psychology. And I
guess, within the UK, there's
always been a sort of difference
between universities in terms of
their focus on teaching, and
research. And I've noticed over
the last few years, actually,
there's a secular shift in terms
of University's engagement with
open research practices. At one
end of the spectrum, you've got
universities such as EU tract
and UCL are very few others are
very much leading the way in
terms of open research and
adopting open research position
statements. Or on the other end
of the extreme, you've got many
universities, who, you know,
think that open research means
no more than open access
publications. And so it's
interesting seeing universities
at different stages of this
journey. And that's one of the
biggest distinctions that I see
between universities at the
moment. And one thing I should
say, if you're interested in
staying within academia, if you
end up in a more research
focused university that hasn't
yet engaged with open research,
or hasn't yet adopted an open
research position statement,
it's actually a great
opportunity to shape it. And you
can put your open leadership
skills you've developed on this
course and practice, you can
kind of educate others about
what openness means to you, and
have that broader discourse. And
one of the challenges I think,
is also having conversations
with people in very different
disciplines. And a couple weeks
time, I'm giving a talk to
colleagues that will include
people with backgrounds in
Humanities Research. So again,
it's just understanding kind of
the language that they use, that
actually describes the same
things that you're interested
in. But just their differences
in terminology. If you end up in
a more teaching focused
institution, it's a great
opportunity as well, to teach
open and reproducible skills to
students. within the UK. It's
interesting to many
undergraduates are now starting
University, having actually had
practice coding in Python and
scratch at school, my daughter
learned how to code in Scratch
when she was about six or seven
years old. So, you know, these
foundational skills in students
are now coming into university
with I guess, within the context
of my own experiences, the
different talk that I would have
given four or five years ago, I
would probably reflect that my
disillusionment with academia,
as much as anything else, you
know, as I'm sure people can
attest to, academia was
certainly was and still is
highly competitive. Some
universities really focused on
big grants, and papers on high
impact journals, rather than
doing robust and reproducible
science. So out of out of my
disillusionment that kind of
encouraged me to engage with the
broader open research and
reproducibility conversations
that were going on on twitter at
the time, you know, two or three
years ago, and coincidentally,
that Coons that occurred when
the UK reproducibility network
was following that. So the UK
reproducibility network funded
by Marcus modaf, who at Bristol
University is focused on
encouraging universities within
the UK to do more reproducible
research, adopt more open
practices. And as a function of
the UK RM developing along with
colleagues at Manchester on
ritual as one of them actually,
we find that the open research
Working Group, which is a
grassroots Working Group, within
academia at Manchester, the
cross disciplines, we've got,
you know, I'm a psychologist,
computer scientists, we've got
biologists, we've got
biostatisticians. We've got
people in the social sciences as
well.
I think that's one of the really
important things to do. It's
actually to build a community
that crosses those traditional
academic disciplines. And one
thing that's very useful about
the open research writing group
activity that we're all engaged
in is it really raises the
profile of open research and
reproducibility within the
university. The university knew
that they needed to do more to
promote open and reproducible
research practices, but they
didn't know how to do it. So the
VP for research at Manchester
has been hugely supportive of
what we've been doing because in
a sense, we're doing the hard
work. We're actually getting The
community started, we're getting
the conversations going. So I
set on the university level,
open research Strategy Group.
Because up until even when I
joined, the group have mainly
focused on open access side of
things because they weren't
really sure what open research
was apart from that. So think
finding your community is really
important or creating a new
community, within your academic
environment, it's important as
well. One thing that's critical,
no matter what career stage
you're at, is try to find some
senior academics in your home
institution who will effectively
be vocal supporters for you and
introduce you to people, I had a
lot of luck at Manchester.
Because I discovered the SSI the
software Sustainability
Institute has been
transformative for both my
career and my mental well being,
I have to say, so meeting people
in the context of the SSI has
been fantastic. And having you
know, somebody like Carl,
Google, or somebody to go and
talk to, and ask for advice is
just fantastic as well, because
Carl is just a hugely important
than financial and wonderful
mentor to have. And just as
these more senior academics will
amplify your voice, it's always
important to remember that you
can amplify the voice of others
in your community. And you
should do that, because there
are always voices that we can,
we can amplify because of our
positions that we're in. So just
to finish off early wants you to
kind of recognize the fact that
you've all got a very unique
skill set. You've got
discipline, specific knowledge,
as well as knowledge about the
kind of computational tools
needed for openness, and
reproducibility. And actually,
not many people have the skills
and certainly not many senior
academics have the skills
either. So in academia, showing
that you're somebody who can
actually solve problems in new
ways, and are those solutions
aligned with young girls and
five years is really powerful
ability to demonstrate. And you
could end up being you know,
almost the go to collaborator
for other academics, wanting to
adopt up and reproducible
practices. So my final three
points I'm just gonna, I'm just
gonna make this probably applies
outside academia as well. Be
aware of institutional politics,
but try not to get involved, if
you can help it. And the other
thing I really say it's at the
end of the day, it's just the
job and make sure that you've
got life and interests outside
of your work.