Unknown: So talk about open
protocols, and really open
methods as a whole within the
context of open research. So
when you think about research we
have researchers doing in this
instance, he has some kind of
lab research, but it may not be
lab research. And we do quite
well. And there's been a lot of
initiatives about making sure we
have access to the research
papers, to the code and the data
and even the citations, but
there hasn't been anywhere near
the same level of focus on
making sure that we actually
have open methods all the time.
So whatever is in the paper, if
the papers open access, then
you'll have access to what part
of methods is presented in the
paper. But that may not actually
be very comprehensive. And so if
we start thinking about
reproducibility of research, and
what it is that it's important
to have as open for research,
the data is great. But if you
don't know how you actually
derive the data, it's not as
helpful as you think in terms of
actually figuring out how it was
generated and what it means
because you don't necessarily
know how it was generated. As
lubei. Why should we care. And
reproducibility in research has
had a lot of really bad, bad
press in recent years. Some
people talk about crisis of
reproducibility. I'm not a big
fan of the crisis terminology,
because I think this is
something that we can easily
address. But it's clearly if not
a crisis, it's still a big
problem. So these tweets that
I'm showing kind of exemplify
the issue. So in the one in the
center, the person is biologist
was looking for a protocol in a
published paper. And that paper
cites an earlier paper. And the
other paper cites on earlier
paper, which cites another
earlier paper, and this is going
to be pre online content for the
most part, and then maybe
eventually, you hit a paywall,
and you just can't access that
information. So in that
instance, this researcher was
getting very frustrated. And so
the, the tweet shows this really
nicely as they tossed the laptop
out the window. It may be that
previous experimental
information only in the real
kind of details of it might only
be in someone else's lab, but
from years before, and that
might have had many coffee
spills, or being torn or lost or
just be illegible, essentially,
by the time you come to look at
it. But that you know, and
scrolling through someone else's
handwritten notes is not a task,
clicking that anyone would
relish it thinking about doing.
But it's not just biological
sciences. So the tweet on the
right is trying to physicists to
hit exactly the same problem of
trying to get to information
about how devices were
fabricated. And conventional
methods in the end was the
answer, which is not helpful to
anybody particularly. And there
have been some big initiatives
in recent times to see if
researchers could replicate and
reproduce some of the results
from some published studies. So
this is a big study by the OSF
Tim Harrington at the OSF and
they, they set out to try and
replicate and reproduce the
results that were arrived at in
50 published papers about cancer
research, as this quote here
shows, which is from the
Atlantic a really nice article
in The Atlantic by Ed young. And
it turned out that it was really
hard to find any of the details
or sufficient amount of
information about the methods in
those papers in order to
reproduce them. So the part that
I've bolded that often, those
recipes are incomplete, missing
out important steps, details or
ingredients. And in some cases,
the recipes aren't described at
all. One of the researchers
actually called this a hopeless
slog. And the the initiative was
stopped after they'd only tried
18 out of the 50 studies,
because it was just impossible.
And it was proving incredibly
expensive as well, to actually
try and perform these
replication studies. So long
story short, is there's a big
problem actually getting to the
methods information about how
people were performing their
research. And that's where
protocols.pi o comes in, which
is the company that I work for.
So we are a for profit, but the
content that we publish is all
open access. And our mission is
really simple. It's a make it
easy to share method details
before, during and after
publication. And it's completely
free to use as well if you're
publishing your content, so
anyone can come sign up for an
account and put in the details
of their experiments, their
protocols. And it looks like a
recipe I'll show you in a
moment. And it's really very,
very user friendly. So if anyone
hasn't had a look, that URL at
the top with slash welcome is a
good place to start to poke
around in there. And it's really
versatile. It was started out
for lab, bench work biological
sciences, but people use it now
in all research disciplines
pretty much.
And here's an example of what
one looks like. So when it's
published, it pretty much does
look like a recipe but also a
little bit like a publication.
So at the top here, you can
hopefully see there's a dry on
this published, published
article. So that means that
you've got a permanent URL link
to a pub initial version that
will stay static. And it's the
implement sure that's used for
all kinds of publishing
research. Essentially. These can
be your your protocols, you can
keep them private to you don't
need to make them public and
give them do it. So you can work
on them with your colleagues and
fiddle faddle around as you
develop them and optimize them,
share them with your team, as
you're working on making them
perfect, before you're ready to
publish them. They are amazing
for reproducibility. They're so
rich in the metadata that can be
added. And people can when
they've been published, if they
repeat an experiment, they can
take, they can kind of press
this works for me button, which
shows that someone else has
managed to replicate the study.
It's incredibly interactive,
people can comment so it's great
for teamwork, others can comment
and access and there can be full
on discussions on the protocol
questions about it. And what's
happening for entrepreneurs to
try and move. videos around
because I'm blocking the slides
for myself. And the do II is
something that you can drop into
your research article. And I'll
show you how you might do that
in a minute. But what's really
brilliant about that is that you
can also create new versions. So
after you've published your
protocol, if you spot a mistake
down the line and want to update
it or clarify something, it's
become clear, it's not very easy
for someone to follow, then you
create a new version. And if
people follow the link from the
published paper, they will see
that there's a new version. So
in I'll just give you a couple
of examples of papers with
protocols in them. So this is a
plus genetics paper actually
contains links to 42 individual
protocols. So when you've got a
really method, heavy paper, you
can create a protocol for every
single one of those. And so each
of these green do I links in the
materials and methods of the
paper points to its own
individual protocol and
protocols to it. And we always
have the journal article link in
there as well. So the two things
are really well interlinked with
one another are 42 individual
ones is a lot, a better way of
doing that might have been to
create a collection. So this is
another example, for a plus
biology paper, where the authors
did exactly that they made a
collection of protocols, and at
the top of their materials and
methods, they link to the
collection goi in protocols.io.
And when you follow that link,
you get taken to this screenshot
that's on the right, which is
telling you exactly what I
mentioned is possible before
that there's a newer version of
the collection available. So
that means the authors have made
some changes and updated it. And
if you click through, you can
see the newer version. What's
also really nice is that you
have very easy ability to
compare versions. So if you want
to see what it was that they
changed, you'll be able to do
that. And it works just like
really a word track change,
where you can see the two side
by side, and highlighted text of
the pieces that have been
updated and changed. So I call
this dynamic permanence because
you can have your published
paper in a journal with the link
to the protocol. But because you
can update the protocol really
easily. The di gives you this
permanent link out to a much
more dynamic document that can
be really a living document and
you can update it. But also
means you don't have to go to
the publisher for a correction.
If you realize there's a mistake
in the method after you've
published it, you can simply
layer on a new version in
protocols IO.
And why they would you do it
this way, rather than having a
you know much more detailed
materials and methods. I think
it's just it's so much richer to
use an online tool that's more
dynamic. So another user can
come in once you've published
your protocol, and run it
actually run through the
protocol in a step by step
manner, which is what this
little movie shows here. You can
add figures and photos and
videos kind of how too much more
of a step by step guide on how
to run the protocol, the kinds
of things that you'd never be,
you wouldn't even be allowed to
put them into a research paper,
you can make this much more of a
how to guide. And it's just has
the capacity to hold a lot more
granular information about
reagents, equipment, specific
tips and tricks on how you made
it work. Maybe it took you a
really long time to work out the
method of kind of shaking and
temperature change and things to
do to make a step of a protocol
work. And there's the
versioning. And it's really just
much better suited than writing
a narrative paragraph that you
would have as materials and
methods in the paper. But also
it's always open access. So I
mean, we are moving towards a
more open access world for
manuscripts, but right now
they're not all open. But if
you've chosen to make the
methods open, at least if the
paper ends up paywalled people
will still be able to get to the
method details without having to
worry about accessing a journal
article. And we have done some
really good kind of community
workspaces which are amazing
actually. And this one was
really organic and it was a neat
idea to create this Coronavirus
method development community,
right at the start of 2020 when
we started receiving submissions
about Coronavirus, various
different techniques, sequencing
or viral load on all sorts of
different things. And we created
this community is probably the
largest growing one and fastest
growing one we've had very
organically so. So it's amazing
to see how thin kind of find
like minded scientists working
on similar things and create
really a huge resource in this
open way. That's really I mean,
the pandemic is, at least the
silver lining is shining a huge
spotlight on the need for more
open science and understanding
and sharing of information as we
make advances as quickly as
possible. And so we were
thrilled to be able to support
these efforts and had our
editorial team helped pull in
protocols when scientists didn't
perhaps have time to do that.
And making the methods protocols
open on their own, makes them a
lot more discoverable
independently of the manuscript.
So the example I'm showing here,
the top left tweet was someone
looking for a protocol to do
with RNA extraction from primary
cortical neuron cultures. So
neuron cells, brain cells, after
several tweets, a UCSF postdoc,
I think it was suggested a
protocol that was on
protocols.io. And actually, when
you click through, you see that
that protocol came from a Giga
science paper, and it was a
paper on three spined
stickleback parasites. So it's
pretty unlikely that a
connection would have been made
between neuron cultures, brain
cells, and someone's work on
stickleback parasites, fish
parasites, without that method
being pulled apart in a modular
way outside of the paper itself.
So sort of this, this modular
approach to open science has
really facilitated discovery and
also research connections with
people who use similar
methodologies, but in completely
different contexts. So having
that as an open piece of
research on its own as a
research output that's
important, independently of
everything else, has made a big
difference in some instances for
people getting the right
feedback on what they should do,
basically. So yeah, I mean, I'm
a huge Open Science advocate all
around. And really, anything you
share, like this can accelerate
science, increase
discoverability,
reproducibility, help you make
good research connections,
enables the reuse. And it really
does enhance the value of the
research, there's really not a
negative reason, I think or
negative outcome from sharing
methods this way. And it's and
it helps with the stewardship of
research output too. So within a
lab, often, it's said that your,
your most likely future
collaborator will be you in six
months time. So if you store the
details in a much better format
than your own scribbled lab
notebook, you're actually making
life easier for yourself in the
future, too. We have a lot of
support, I realize I'm running
out of time from journals and
publishers and funders, and also
institutions, who also recommend
people use protocols that I owe.
So we're very happy to help
people if they're interested in
using the tool. And it's only a
small company, Lenny, who people
may or may not know is our
founder. And Anita has been
there for a while too. And it's
Thank you very much. Now, many,
many questions I'm getting at,
I'm quite aware of time, but
that is that folks are really,
really enthusiastic about what
you've said. And there are
questions about integration
about DUIs. versioning. So if
you if you could take a bit of
time, sorry, I have to ask this.
But yeah, if you could take a
bit of time on the hacker days
and maybe put some answers
there. That would be really,
really helpful for us.
We don't have to go ahead and do
that after this. That's an
impromptu so much. Thank you.
Yeah, so I'm gonna pass to y'all
for the closing.
I've managed to find the unmute
button in time. Okay, so this
has been jam packed full, but
really, really quite an exciting
call. I'm in love with how on
fire the questions were also for
this last talk. So for now, we
did have a fourth speaker
planned, we wouldn't have had
time for them even if they had
been able to make it. But
thankfully, we have a video so
right now online for four five
of the hack MD. We suggest just
hop over when you have some time
that doesn't have to be now and
just have a look at bastions
talk about citizen science which
is another open The science
method that's really important.
And apart from that, we actually
have a an optional cohort course
next week for self care and ally
skills. I know we normally have
a week off in between. But next
week, we have another call. We
will send out more info about
that. But you should have
received the calendar invite the
heck MD has been a pain in the
rear today. I'm really sorry
about that. We are going to
evaluate what's going on and
figure out whether it's still
the best option. And there is
more room for any other feedback
if you want to throw any
feedback right at the very, very
bottom of the document if
there's any feedback you'd like
to share, but we are four
minutes over so I am going to
say thank you very much. It's
been delightful, and we will see
you again later. Bye. Oh and
thanks so much. Thank you