Unknown: My name is Kimberly
Pasha, and I work as research
funder for Wellcome Trust. So,
this is not what I have always
done in my career path. And I
would like to start by giving
you a quick overview of how
Actually, I like how my career
path has unfolded, like over the
past almost 15 years. And I also
would like to share with you
perhaps top three highlights
over this path, as well as my
top three mistakes, because I
think they're also important.
And I really hope that these may
somehow inspire some ideas and
trigger questions that we can
hopefully discuss later on
during the q&a session. So I
spent my the majority of my
career in academic research and
in so called the wet lab
settings, I graduated from my
undergrad in genetics at
University of Edinburgh. And at
that point in my life, I was
very much into sales, and, and,
you know, genetics and basically
model organisms, so everything
had to matter at a microscopic
level. So, with all this love
for genetics and cells, I ended
up by getting a PhD in cellular
biology, and more specifically,
I worked on insulin signaling
pathway in fruit fly Drosophila.
And then pretty much right after
I graduated from my PhD, I
started a postdoc at University
College London. And I still
wanted to get my beloved model
organism, Drosophila and my
signaling pathway. But I started
getting more interested in the
effects as an organism level and
overpopulation. So my postdoc
research focused on the effects
of insulin on aging, and
lifespan control and Drosophila.
And I guess my focus somehow
upgraded from the macro level to
a macro level, because I was
done looking at longevity in
populations. But I remember that
at some point, throughout my
postdoc, I realized that if I
was sustained academia, then
that one specific question was
probably going to be what I was
going to build the rest of my
career upon, and it would be
very difficult to pivot
significantly down the line. And
somehow that really didn't sit
well with me. And with my
personality, I really missed
having a broad overview of a
research landscape and having
the flexibility to change
interests significantly.
Whenever I, you know, I felt
that it was needed. And since I
was also working at the very
much discovery end of things,
the impact of the outputs was
very hard to observe, which also
kind of demotivate demotivated
me. So then I thought about what
I needed to change. So I wanted
to have a job which allowed me
to have a broader view over
biomedical research, shorter
timeline to impact and also
something with the people factor
that enabled me to network and,
and engage and, and basically,
with people. So I apply for a
job as Portfolio Manager at
welcome, which I was then
offered. And I changed my career
probably after 10 years in
academic research. And actually,
I also very much recently
changed my job from Portfolio
Manager. And I started working
as a data challenges manager
with in the same team as yo. So
somehow, even within the
research funding landscape, my
job very much recently changed.
So as part of my current job, I
will keep an strategic overview
of the Global Health Research
landscape. And with main, my
main focus being the health
data, I look out for
opportunities to advance
welcomes mission as a funder.
And also I create networks, I
engaged with the research
community and other research
funding stakeholders, I build
partnerships, I enable platforms
to improve health globally. And
overall, I have to say it is
actually quite exciting. And so
then I guess that Oh, okay,
maybe like one thing I have to
add at that point is, and the
kind of somehow the power
dynamics, I was involved and
changed quite a lot as well,
ever since I shifted from being
a researcher and I started
working for a funder. In a way I
was at this end of the spectrum,
where I was constantly asking
for money to fund my research.
And now I, I became part of this
organization, where this kind of
decisions are made. And if I'm
fully honest, I do actually
really enjoy this change in
dynamics
is a is an easier place to be,
you know, in all honesty, and
Okay, so then when I thought
about three highlights from the
past 15 years, I think it is
really important to acknowledge
this intellectual freedom and
space for curiosity that
academic research has enabled me
I think, I think that's, that's
really that's a that's a
phenomenal opportunity, I have
to say, and, and similarly, this
kind of analytical skills that
one acquires while doing
research are so transferable and
I think at that time, I was
totally undressed. demanding it.
But the day that you end up at a
kind of a normal business
meeting with people, and you can
use your skills and backup where
arguments in a similar way that
you would back up your
scientific hypothesis with data,
you realize that it's actually
very transferable. And it's
actually quite cool to see that.
And I think the highlight of
being research funder is this
ability to influence the wider
landscape. And that also happens
even at a quite junior level,
you don't have to be the
director of something. And, and
it is nice to see this, this
short timeline to impact about
something that you really care
about. And three things I wish I
had done differently. I really
wish I had had a less linear
career path in academic research
in the way I went from 1pm. Like
from finishing the PhD right
into a postdoc, like, you know,
it seemed like everything had to
happen pretty quickly. And I
think that was a mistake, I
think I should have really had a
much more awkward facing
approach to things. And and the
second thing is, I think it is
okay to be picky. Like, if
someone offers you interesting
job in a good lab, it doesn't
mean that you have to take it
you need to think about it in
the wider context of career
progression, because it is
important. And also, finally,
when I was an academic
researcher, I really wish I had
done more investments into
secondary skills and I had
thought a little bit broader
than just you know, getting my
research done getting my papers
published. I think it will
definitely help me. Okay, so I
am going to stop here and thank
you for listening