Unknown: Hi, everyone. I'm
Melissa. I'm now a training and
communications officer with
Australian buyer comments, but I
used to be at the FBI. But the
reason I'm here today is that I
have been quite heavily involved
with an alexian working group on
making training materials fair.
And some of the other people on
the call have also been involved
in that. So to begin with the
end, this project that I'm going
to talk you through has been a
massive collaborative effort.
It's started as a legacy of by a
hackathon project in 2018. And
then it was taken on by the
Alexia working group for making
for making training materials
fair, which led to the
publication of 10 simple rules
for making training materials
fair and plus computational
biology. And I'll share the link
to that with you in in the chat
and in the documents later on.
So I think Philips talk was
quite a nice segue into this
because he's already started to
talk about some of the types of
training materials. And when we
said about doing this work, we
first had to define really, what
are we talking about when we're
talking about training
materials. And we took a really
broad view of this of it being
any digital object that you use
in training. So this can be
PowerPoint slides, it can be
data sets, it can be PDF,
handouts, it can be whatever you
think of that you can use in
training, we excluded physical
things that you might use for as
fer is directed towards a
digital environment. Okay, so
why do we need to be fair when
we're thinking about training
materials. So the key thing that
you do as a trainer, when you
start to plan for your event is
to develop the materials that
you're going to present. And
when you do this, then some of
the common things that people do
is to go and look at what's
already out there for
inspiration. Once you've done
that, you might decide to build
your own materials. And you
might, or you might completely
reuse somebody else's materials
are just bits and pieces from
other China ours China's
material as well, because it
makes it faster. But it also
means that what you are teaching
is consistent with what other
people are teaching within your
field. And it makes it more
efficient. But what we've all
found as trainers as that this
can be quite hard. And in
particular, it's really hard to
find training materials. But
then it's also really hard to
understand what people have done
with those training materials
because there isn't enough
metadata to describe them. We've
also found that once you find
the materials, they can be
inaccessible. So you know, it's
there that you can't get access
to it, or they're not licensed
for reuse as well. Now, we
realized that these are
challenges that are also
apparent with data. And we knew
about the principles that
Philips just told us about. So
we decided to try and repurpose
those principles for the
purposes of training materials.
And this theory, lots and lots
of conversation and lots of
discussion has led us to
building these these 10 simple
rules or 10 simple steps towards
making training materials fit.
And they're really they're not
hard and fast rules, they're
more like guidelines to get you
thinking about what you need to
do. So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to walk through each
of these 10 steps at quite a
high level. And then if you want
to know about any of the
particular steps in more detail,
we can talk about that more as
well. So number one is to share
your materials, this is going to
sound really obvious, but it is
one thing that people don't
think about. And of course, if
you don't share your materials,
nobody else is going to be able
to find them. It's also really
important to to plan for sharing
your materials. So as you're
creating them think about
writing down those bits of
metadata and things that you
need in order to explain it to
other material. But also think
about where you're going to
share them and how that
influences the fairness of your
materials. And there are lots of
different places that you can
share your materials and denodo
as we just saw is one of those
places. GitHub is also a popular
place that lots of people have
been using recently. Okay, so
second step on the road to
fairness is to describe the
training materials properly. So
for this particular step, we
were more thinking about
structuring the metadata rather
than what goes into the
metadata. And this is really to
make it easier for search
engines to find and to index,
the content of your materials.
So one of the ways you can do
this is to use bio schemas. So
bio schemas have specifications
that have certain categories
that are associated with
training materials. The other
thing You can do is to use an
keywords from an ontology to
describe your materials more
consistently. So that within
your field, so say, I'm training
here in Australia and somebody
else's training over in the UK,
we're both describing training
materials on the same topic with
the same words. Within the
bioinformatics community, quite
a lot of people are using terms
from the EDM ontology. And you
can go and look that up on the
MLS ontology lookup service, if
you're more interested to know
what's in that. So So step
three, and this is going to be
sounding quite familiar from
what we've just heard is to give
your training materials a unique
identity. So one of the identity
persistent identifiers you can
use here is a do II. And often
if you're sharing through things
like zenodo, it will
automatically be given into your
line. Again, you can also
encourage the use of P IDs for
authors by using orchids. And by
doing this, you're making sure
that you get credit for the work
that you've done, and any
contributors are also getting
credit. And this helps build
your reputation as a trainer as
well. Okay, so step four is to
register your materials online.
Now, this might sound like the
same thing as step one that is
actually slightly different. So
in step one, we're talking about
getting your materials out as
uploading them somewhere.
Whereas this one is more about
collecting materials from the
same topic together into a
registry. So you're telling a
website that I have materials
out there, this is where you can
find them. So for
Bioinformatics, there's a couple
of different examples of this,
there's elixirs tests, and there
is also the goblet portal for
training materials. And they're
kind of aggregating all those
different training materials
together into one place so that
they're easier to find. And then
they will link out to where they
are stored. Number five is to
define the access rules. So the
level of accessibility of
different materials can vary for
many different reasons. It may
be that your materials are, for
example, only accessible to
people who've paid for that
course. Now, that's completely
fine. As Phillip was saying, the
level of accessibility can vary,
you just have to be very clear
about how it varies and what the
rules for access are. And what
we recommend that you do is to
to write this in the metadata or
to even include it in a readme
file that goes alongside your
training materials. So people
can very clearly see whether or
not they can access the
materials and how they can do
it. Next step is to use an
interoperable format. This one I
think, was one of the most
controversial things that we
discussed when we tried to think
about what these are also, they
can see photos grinning, because
he was there for these
discussions. For training
materials, I think the format
that you choose really depends
on your context and what you
intend to use it for. However,
you should be aiming to use a
format that can be used in
different contexts and on
different operating systems. And
use a format that is editable if
you want to enable it to be
fair. So there's lots of
different formats out there. For
example, just for presentations,
you've got PDFs, PowerPoints,
and latex. And each of these
have different advantages and
different disadvantages, and
some are more adaptable than
others. If you want to have a
closer look at the advantages
and disadvantages of those types
of formats, then we have a nice
table in the paper that looks at
those in detail. also noted here
that there is now a trend
towards providing training
materials in markdown. It's
becoming very popular, and it
does have great uses in certain
contexts. Okay, so number seven,
is making the materials reusable
for trainers. And in contrast
the data what we're actually
doing it here is targeting
people rather than machines. So
for a trainer to be able to take
somebody else's materials and
reuse them, they need to be able
to understand what that material
was trying to deliver, why, and
how. And all of this information
needs to be included in the
metadata. And ideally, that
metadata could be structured as
well, we'd make it even easier
to find.
In order for trainers to be able
to reuse the materials as we saw
earlier as well, you need to
give it a license that allows
that reuse. So the Creative
Commons licenses are great for
this. And there are different
levels of licensing that you can
apply depending on your own
situation. So number eight,
there is another group of people
who might want to reuse training
materials and This is the
Chinese themselves. So when you
want to learn something for
yourself, but you don't have
time to go on a course, one
thing you might do is go out
onto the internet and look for
things that are already out
there. So that you can teach
yourself. I just saw your
stretching, I thought she was
very excited about that. That's
just stretching. Right? So for
trainees, they're coming at it
from a slightly different angle,
and they want to know as well
what the training is about. But
they want to know, specifically,
what are they going to get out
of this training, and what do
they need to know in advance, in
order for them for it to be the
right training for them. So in
your metadata of with your
training materials, you should
always be including learning
outcomes and prerequisites. And
as we're saying, again, again,
the way you write this is really
important, and you should aim to
be using a consistent format.
What's being recommended in the
training sphere, and in the
education world as well is to
use the format of an active
verb, ideally, from a Bloom's
ontology, or taxonomy rather,
plus a behavior, knowledge,
skill or ability. So for
example, if we were to apply
that to this presentation, we'd
say by the end of this
presentation, you should be able
to list which is your verb, the
10 simple steps to making
training materials fair, which
is the knowledge part of that
equation. Nine, so number nine
is training doesn't occur in a
bubble. When you're developing
training materials, you always
seek feedback from others, and
you always can welcome
contributions as well, it's
always very helpful, that there
are steps that you can take to
make this more open. So you can
start by telling people how they
can contribute to your
materials. And when you're doing
this to use a warm tone.
alongside your metadata you can
can include a contribution file,
and I'm pretty sure you learned
about this in one of the past
sessions. And in this year,
you're stating the rules for
participation and contribution.
So you're telling people how
they contribute what you want
control contributions on and
what they're going to get out of
it as well. Of course, if other
people are contributing to you
materials, you want to give
credit where credit's due, that
is only the fair thing in
another context. Okay, so I feel
like I'm speaking quite fast.
And we've come to number 10,
which is very important, as
well, and often forgotten is to
keep your materials out tonight.
It's great. If you're sharing
materials, and you're putting
them out there. However, the
materials go out of date. And
this is okay, if your materials
are out of date, and you don't
have time to update them, that's
fine. Just add a note to the
metadata saying that they've
been retired and there shouldn't
be used anymore for these
reasons. However, if you want to
continue to use your materials,
and you're updating them, make
sure that you're keeping track
of the versions and that it's
easy for people to identify,
which is the most recent version
as well. There's different ways
that you can do this and it's
some level it depends on where
you're sharing your materials as
well. And many people on the
call are going to be great
champions of GitHub for this as
well but there are other options
too. Okay, so that was quite a
quick whistlestop tour of the
kind of thinking that this the
elixir working group came to
when we put together the 10
simple rules 10 simple steps
towards making training
materials fair. If you have any
questions and we'll come to take
them happy to take them now.
Okay, talk about them in the
breakout rooms as well. Also pop
a link to the slide into the
paper in into the chat and to
the document in a moment.