Unknown: My name is Omar from
Africa Chi cheery currently
based in Malaysia. We are here
to share with you what a
preference is. And in the
context of open science.
Particularly my talks will be
focused more on the African
preference Saba, which is Africa
archive, which is the largest, I
mean, the only African preprint
server that we have. I am
actually a PhD student recently
got my PhD two months ago. I'm
affiliated with Africa archive,
being a moderator there and also
a bioinformatics coordinator
with science, communication,
health Nigeria, and also a
secretary to the Nigerian
bioinformatics and genomics
network. Before start, Ellie
just wants to share with you
what the preprint servers are.
The preprint servers actually
called a cluster of computers,
where scientists or researchers
are like, from different
disciplines up and share them,
their manuscripts publicly
available to community for
accessibility. So we do have
different kinds of Saba based on
the disciplines that you fall
in. The most popular ones, if
you are in biology is the bio
archive, which is based in
united states currently been
hosted by called herbosophy
laboratories. And you can choose
from where you wanted to deposit
based on your fields beat
pharmacology, pathology,
biology, microbiology can choose
the, the preference you may want
to submit your manuscript to. We
also have are the kind of
archive that holds natural
sciences like Mathematics and
Computer Sciences, as well as
quantitative biology. And in the
context of medical lines, we do
have med archive, which covers
those in public health and
Occupational and Environmental
Health, they usually the
positive manuscripts, they're
wild. For chemistry, they have
Chem archive, where you can also
deposit your research work.
While in the African continent,
we have Africa archive, where we
accept all kinds of
publications, as well as data
sets in the print language
within the continent of Africa.
This is so because some
scientists in Africa
particularly they do a kind of
reset with their languages,
local languages, and those
languages timeout actually
visible. Because some of the
journals that are published are
within the African countries are
mostly not online, they're
actually being printed in
hardcopy forms. So we thought of
coming up with this applicant
archive so that we can help
scientists to discover more
African scientists for maybe
collaborations and visibility.
So what is a preference? A
preference is actually a
complete scientific documents
that you may have a manuscript
so to call back, you can
publicly share our make it
available online freely, to be
accessible by communities of
scientists and researchers
alike. And it has some actually
associated benefits. Like you
can get cited before your
manuscript is being rebuilt in
the journals. You can also be
exposed people will get to know
you, especially nowadays that
most of the free prints they
usually have a Twitter handles
are each day, share your
research online, and people will
get to know you get to know your
publications. And you get you
will likely get funders and
I'm saying to be collaborators
as well. And you can also get
some feedback. If you get I
mean, if the paper maybe need
some corrections or other
things, scientists will give you
some kind of feedback before
your manuscript is clearly built
by the journals that you
submitted to. And also it will
be freely available and having a
DUI. You can get cited as I
mentioned. So we have free
prints repositories. They
actually basically divided into
two which preference and pause
prints. The name implies,
preference is just the complete
manuscripts that you have an
publicly shared before peer
reviewed journals, while the
first print is actually research
articles, that is peer reviewed
and accepted for publications.
So I want to make an emphasis
that A preprint publishing a
preprint is not actually
published in journals. So, you
may want to like, check out
romea to check whether it is
allowed by the journal that you
wanted to submit your manuscript
is allow you to submit the
buttons of your paper in a
preference others are not. So it
is actually advisable for
scientists to make use of this
opportunity is freely online,
you can check it and make use of
the website ShareFile romea. And
then you can keep the titles of
the journals, maybe you can key
in maybe something like genome
biology or nature dependence on
the targeted journals that you
wanted to submit your manuscript
to. And it will give you the
details policy with which the
journals is having so that it
will guide to whether to submit
your manuscript to preference or
not. So there is a number of
those African as preprint
servers around which are
basically being a partnership
with Open Science Center for
Open Science, there are options
infrastructure, and there are
regionals and some discipline
specific reference repositories.
So, you can see Africa archive
is also known among the open
source infrastructure around. So
in Africa archive, what we do is
basically, we we provide a
platform for submissions of
multiple publications format. As
I mentioned before, you can
submit your data set your
presentations, your proposals
and your manuscript as well or
even review papers, because we
got to realize that some
preference like by archives,
they don't accept to submitted
proposals or to submit a review
paper or something like that.
But in African archive, we allow
scientists around the African
countries to submit these kinds
of words, because we want to
make it we want to make them
globally known, and people get
to know them. So they can have
collaboration sometimes. So we
also promote the use of local
languages. In that, we do have a
kind of if we have researched
with the local language, we make
sure that we translated the
abstract into English passion so
that global scientific community
can have access. We also build
collaborations and increase our
current research visibility
across the gloves, also built
and customized to fulfill the
needs of African researchers.
And we do all these in
partnership with zenodo, Open
Science Framework and open
publications as well as signs up
and to us. It's like our own
repository before we built our
own personal repository. We do
that to increase visibility and
discoverability, across the
Africa and globally. Together,
we also have a partnership with
fraserview. Science upon PCI for
reviewing the contents of the
manuscript that is submitted to
Africa archive, recently have
also partnership with fiction
and public knowledge,
public knowledge project. So
what we accept in African
archives, we allow African
scientists based in the
continent of Africa to submit
their work to also allow African
scientists who are currently
please like me at other
institutions outside Africa to
also submit their manuscripts
there. And also non African
scientists who report on
research conducted in African
territory, preferably with
African co authors listed and
then we also allow non African
scientists who report on
research related to African
Affairs. So here Our team of
curators and community
developers, as well as site
maintainence, who are actually
maintaining the upper concave
side. And we also have a lot of
advisory boards, we have Joyce
who is the the executive
director of of training for
psycho science in sorry,
Training Center in
communications in Africa. So we
have Mahmud who is the Executive
Director for science
communication, hope and African
literacy science network, whom
we put in place as both advisory
boards to the to be given some
kind of advice and directions on
African archive. So we have
multiple channels of
communications, in which you can
Get in touch with us. If you are
from Africa or if you are
African researchers, you can get
in touch with us through our
Twitter handles, email address.
We also have a slack channels
where you can get in touch with
us by institutions. Are we also
looking for collaborations from
other institution?