Unknown: Hi, everyone, it's
really great to be here. Can you
see my slides at all? Or not?
Oh, yes. Can we saw them? Sorry.
Oh, sorry, I okay, because I
couldn't see the green frame
round my window. I thought it
didn't work. It's perfect. Okay,
so my name is Alex Savage. I'm
the training team lead at the
software Sustainability
Institute. I'm based in
Manchester and I'll be talking
to you a bit about open
scientific code in research. big
thank you to yo for borrowing
her slides. From her workshop on
how to contribute to open
source. There is a link to that
workshop as well, if you want
to, to visit, she made my life
much easier. So I just modified
her slides slightly. Big, big
thank you. Okay, so what what do
we mean, when we say, open
source? The first thing to know
is that open source is not the
same thing as being free. So you
have some free software, which
is an open source, so it's free
to download, you can you can,
it's free to use, however, you
download some binary executable,
you don't get to see modify or
reuse the source code itself. On
the other side, you also have
some open source software, which
isn't free, it doesn't happen
very often. But for example, you
have, you have software which is
made openly available, however,
sometimes you have to pay for
support from the team, or some
extra help. So even though the
source the source, the software
is open, you still have to pay
for some services. However,
there is intersection between
the two where you have open
source software that is also
free to use. So what is open
source sexually, it's simply
sharing the design of your work
so that it can be reused and
remixed by others. And it can be
anything, we are talking about
open source code, however, it
can be a methodology that you
can make publicly open. It can
be an algorithm, it can be data,
it can be your photos, it can be
anything that you're working on.
Why should you use and promote
open source source, so just a
bit on motivation. So the first
thing is that once you make your
work or your your, your code
public, it can be peer reviewed
and reused by others. So you get
second pair of eyes, you get
more users for your code, there
is something that we call hacker
ethic where, which means nobody
should have to reinvent the
wheel, if you benefited from
someone else's work, you should
give back to the community by
making your work open as well.
This is also making the science
advance faster, because people
don't have to redo the same
thing all over again. It also
helps you get more from the
community so you can collaborate
with more people who might be
distributed around the world. So
you share your work others share
back and it's it's a bit of a
back and forth interaction. And
ultimately, you want your work
and research to to be
reproducible by others, and
making your code and your data
and your methodology open is the
first step on that on that road.
Again, a bit of motivation, why?
Why would you want to make your
code and your work open, there
is a risk associated with with
with a closed code. So perhaps
the picture on the top is, if
you've probably seen it recently
because it puts a spotlight on
on research code during the
pandemic. So the picture on top
is an mathematical
epidemiologist Neil Ferguson
from the Imperial College. So
they his team, they had a
software on modeling pandemics,
and the software was in
existence over the at least past
10 years. However, it was only
made widely publicly available
in March this year. And of
course, because of the wider
scrutiny it was spot on under
under a magnifying glass loads
of loads of bugs were uncovered.
So perhaps and then the team
perhaps unfairly received loads
of criticism. Now, this is not
the criticism of anyone's codes.
What the point I'm trying to
make is if you release your code
early, and if you release often,
you will get more eyes on it. It
will ultimately improve your
code. We all make mistakes and
there is no code that is that is
bug free. However you shouldn't
be be afraid to make those
mistakes. Get it out there. have
others have a look, it can all
make, it can only make your code
better. It also aids
transparency in research, being
open and publishing your code
and software and data. So, these
top top guidelines for
transparency in research have
been created by a journal
founders in societies. And they
cover not only transparency of
your analytical methods and
software, but anything related
to your research data, your
research plan, all the research
materials, everything, if
possible, always try and make
this open. There are obviously
some constraints, sometimes you
can't publish your data due to
some privacy restrictions. So
over 5000 journals have now
signed up to these top
guidelines, it's getting loads
of traction, you should follow
it too. So how do you know if
software is open source, even if
source code is available and
viewable online, so it's
published somewhere where you
can find it, and you can
technically access it. If there
is not a license associated with
the code, it's not illegal to
reuse it. So that's one of the
most important things if you
wants to make your software
public, you need to have a
license file, stating that it is
in fact legal to for your code
to be reused or remixed in any
way. There are different license
types. It's potentially a
minefield as well. However,
there is loads of help as well
on how to choose your your
license. And once you do it, you
need to specify that under a
filed file, which is named
either a license or license that
txt or licensed attendee, which
is stored in the root of your
open source repository. So make
sure that you always add a
license to your software, or to
data or to photos, or whatever
it is that you publish, if you
want everyone else to use it. So
again, once again, no one can
reuse it unless you give it an
explicit right to do so even in
your in your mind, you're
thinking, Oh, I want to make
this open. until until you have
a license file. It's not legal
to to do so. Okay, so how do you
go about publishing and sharing
your open open code. So the
first steps for publishing and
sharing is version control.
Version Control is a system that
record changes to a set of files
within a folder over time. So
you can recall a specific
version later. It gives you, it
gives you basically two things,
it enables you to publish and
share your code. And also, it
gives you a way to backup and
version control your code. So
you can always go back to a
version, jump back in time, it's
like a time machine for your
code. It's a must have these
days, it gives you as I said, it
gives you both aspects,
publishing and sharing plus
backup and version control. It's
just universally useful. So why
is it? What's it useful for it,
it's going to help you to never
mess up again. Well, okay, it's
not, it's not like you're not
going to mess up. But it's going
to make it easier for you to
recover from your mistakes. If
you overwrite your code or
overwrite your data or make some
make some blunder. It makes
collaborating or code so much
easier. As I said, it also
offers off site backups. Because
you're putting your code in a
centrally central server, you
don't actually have to backup
your code on your external drive
anymore. So for example, if you
work on on your desktop at work,
and then you have your laptop at
home, you don't actually have to
keep copying and backing up your
code and transferring between
these two, you can just easily
sync with the central
repository, and you're good to
go. So what's not to like? Well,
apart from learning how to
actually use a version control
system, which we recommend that
you do.
So Git and GitHub. Git is one
type of a version control
software. It's not the only one,
but it's one that is widely used
today. And then there is GitHub
as well, which is a central site
that costs Git repositories and
also gives you a nice user
interface to get which is under
the hood. There are other tools
similar to Git and GitHub, you
have Mercurial and Bitbucket
some peculiar, Mercurial is a
version control system similar
to Git Bitbucket is similar to
GitHub, a user interface where
you can host your repositories.
There is also Git and GitHub. So
GitHub is just a slightly
different user interface to
GitHub and uses Git underneath.
So at the bottom of the slide,
you have a link to yours get
workshop if you want to have a
look at that. And also we
strongly recommending learning,
some version control system. It
doesn't have to be get, but as I
said, Everyone seems to be Using
it's these days Git and GitHub,
so it's worthwhile, and it will
pay off tenfold. There are loads
of other workshops to help you
learn git, or to get you started
with GitHub. So just a couple of
tips to make your work open
source.
So the first thing I've already
mentioned at the license file,
because unless you have it, it's
not legal to read your code. Try
to avoid jargon, or at least try
to explain it in plain English.
If possible. Edit the readme
file. It's also one of the must
haves to explain what your what
your project is about how it is
used, how you can contribute how
to report bugs, consider having
a roadmap of allowing others to
see what what's in your plans,
and how you can set your
priorities. Contributing guide
if you can, if you want others
to contribute, make a file
called contributing.md in the
root of your repository, and set
up some guidelines for
contributors, so that they know
what they should do if they want
to help you out. issues. GitHub
has issue tracker. And again,
other other version control
software also have issue
trackers to record your bugs and
supply new features. You can
also use tags to make it easy to
sort your issues, have a code of
conduct all good projects have
it too, to make sure that
everyone who contributes and is
part of the project is treated
well and state how violations
will be handled. GitHub has a
code of conduct wizard to make
it easy for you to add one
citation. If you use other
people's software, you should
cite it as well as you cite
their research papers. And
similarly, if you write your
code, you want some credit for
it. So in order to help people
cite your software, add a
citation.md file to your
repository with the suggested
citation how to cite you
consider getting a DUI for your
data or code. It's now possible
either using zenodo or figshare.
And you get to dry and then you
also can use that to site, your
site, your project, your
software project. Also add how
to contact yourself and the
team. And make sure you have
your contact details there as
well. So this is just a quick
cookbook for you to get you
started with with open source
development. The ultimate goal
is full reproducibility. So you
have many open computational
tools around such as our in
Python Jupyter Notebook, our
lab, our studio, we have Git and
GitHub that I mentioned already.
And then you have binder. So
consider container container
rising your software code and
data to allow for full
reproducibility and binder sort
of integrates with all these
other software tools mentioned
above on this slide. So just
some pointers for further
reading and some activities for
you to get you started or to
follow up and where to go from
here, how to contribute to open
source software. So think about
maybe some software that you
like or that you use, consider
maybe checking some issues and
see if you can contribute to
that software. There is also the
first timers only toggle on
GitHub to help you select some
projects which are suitable to
contribute for someone who is
just just new to open source
development. Or there is a
website website called first
timers.com. You can try and
participate in Oktoberfest or
Mozilla global sprint or 24 pull
requests projects. They all
happen throughout the year.
There is just the Journal of
open science software, you can
either submit your software or
Twitter you can apply to be a
reviewer. And finally, a great
training resource on that
hearing where your handbook for
reproducible data science it
covers loads of off the aspects
of open source but it also gives
you the bigger picture on how to
make your research reproducible.
And with that, just want to
thank you, everyone.