Unknown: Today I bring you the
ajl and interactive project
management methods as a topic.
First of all, I would like to
say that I am not an expert on
these topics, but I do use some
of the principles and some of
the ideas that this framework
gives us. So what First of all,
what is actually a trial. So a
trial is a kind of like a
combination of different
techniques with and you might
see some of these keywords
popping around if you google
these terms, you might see Scrum
Kanban, waterfall, and so on.
And, and what these terms kind
of convey are just different
strategies to organize and to
plan a project. The, the Agile
principle, or the Agile kind of
framework also has a manifesto.
And you can find this manifesto
on the Agile manifesto.org
website. And the name itself.
And the process is mostly
focused on delivering content as
quickly as possible to minimize
like bureaucratic steps or
things that are not directly
directly going to produce an
output. And so for instance, the
the emphasis on prototyping and
working solutions rather than
documentation. or, or, for
instance, actually interacting
between people as opposed to
just establishing bureaucratic
processes. And the name itself a
jail is, is in part as a as a
need to respond to change. And
this is something that you will
see often in the business world.
And I'll explain how this kind
of plays in in the next slide.
So if you're if you're familiar
with the the more traditional
way of planning a project, you
have often requirements set up
from from from early stage, then
you have a phase where it just
design and you kind of try to
plan and to think of all the
possible situations where things
can go wrong, or you want to
make sure that you cover all the
cases. And eventually you get to
a step where you actually
implement the plan, you put the
plan into action. And And
afterwards, you validate and you
you kind of have a delivery in
the end. This approach means
that the time that goes between
the start of the concept, all
the way to the delivery of the
product is a very large period
of time. And therefore, it's
considered a high risk kind of
approach. Because you don't
really have anything until many
months later or many years
later, depending what you're
trying to build. To counter that
the HL approach is a little bit
more dynamic. And the focus is
that you have these these kind
of it narrative cycles, where
you focus on milestones you
focus on achieving small goals,
small deliverables. And this
will actually give you a better
notion of progress. And also a
better notion of how, how your
how your, how you are succeeding
in achieving those milestones.
So it gives you both the
progress and something to show
and to and to, to kind of
feedback on. And then from
there, you can also learn what
worked, what didn't work. And
you can kind of go back to
planning and readjust if
anything needs to be done. And
so this is a kind of like a
cyclical process that goes back
and forth. So this process, I
didn't specifically mentioned
this, but this was a kind of a
framework that was designed for
for software development,
primarily, although there's a
lot of things that we can learn
and apply to other projects. And
how do you actually take this to
your project? And how do you
apply it. So you can think of it
as a little bit of a Matryoshka
type situation where, in the
end, the biggest matter you ask
is your final product, this is
what you want to deliver. But
you're going to have to break
down all the tasks that you have
to do you cannot just think of a
project and do it all at once
you're going to have to identify
small steps that you can do. And
the key aspect in the in the
agile approach is actually to
break down these processes in
all these the like, this big
project into milestones that
will be like the intermediate
level materials can in this
case, and and then tasks or even
sub tasks or issues in the in
the case of GitHub, for
instance, where you have smaller
steps that can go between one
and two hours or at most one day
of working, working time. And,
and so how could this be made
into practice so borrowing an
example that that you're set up
from the From the inter mind
project, you can see this kind
of visualization of the of
several different issues. Each
column represents a different
version with an expected
timeline and delivery date. And
then each of these little
bubbles, or you can think of it
as post its as well, that's
where the Kanban kind of concept
comes from, has a bunch of
labels describing what they are,
it has a title, and you
eventually can assign or you can
move things between the panels,
and so on. And the idea is that
with this, you have a very
visual overview of where you are
in the project, what needs to be
done. And you can also
prioritize things by just moving
them up and down in this kind of
visual list. And as soon as
something is complete, then it
can be hidden from this view, or
it can be moved elsewhere. So in
this case, this is, is focused
on version, so each of the
columns is a version. But the
more common approach is actually
to have kind of like stages of
the progress. And here I'm
borrowing the, the project from
my actually, so the awesome Open
Science Montreal project where
they already started using this,
this approach. And you can see
that the GitHub provides this
standard to do in progress and
done and, and you can, you can
see how you can plan things and
leave them on the to do and then
everything that is being worked
on is in the in progress section
with assigned to different
people and so on. And, and one
additional thing, so mentioning
this, this breaking down of
tasks is that with GitHub, you
can have not just issues, but
you can also have within an
issue, you can have, like bullet
points that you can make into
checkboxes. And these will be
recognized as a smaller steps
within that issue that you can
then complete, and, and have as
a initial progress for for the
task. And there's also a way to
somehow automate this process, I
have to be honest, that I'm not
super familiar with this. But if
you if you want, there is a way
to simplify this process
further. And but so in general
terms, what what what are these
issues or what what could you
make into an issue. And so you
can think of For instance, if
you wanted to make a website,
you could try to break it down
into creating content for the
website, as well as Oops, sorry,
as well as creating or finding a
domain to actually have as the
address for your website. And
there, you would have to, for
instance, decide what domain
that would be agreed between
everyone eventually purchase
that domain, and set it up as as
the redirect for the GitHub
account. And, and similarly, you
would have to create the
content, and then the different
parts of actually creating the
content, how you would go about
it and different sections of
your website, and so on. And you
can think of each of these
bullet points as an issue. And
you could even think of these
inner ones as for instance,
these checkboxes that I was
mentioning on on GitHub, for
instance. And so there's also a
live demo that has been set up
by by by the MLS team. Before I
will make sure to add that link
to the to the hack MD and and
I'll add some additional
resources as well if you want to
read a bit more on that.