Unknown: We are going to talk
about open canvas. And this is
another exercise that basically
helps you think through in a
structured way, what you're
going to be doing, by forcing
you to fit all of your ideas
into a tiny a4 sheet.
So,
yeah, open Canvas allows you to
think through your project
strategy. And there are also
some examples available. And we
will ask you to actually finish
this on on your own after the
call. And as I mentioned, we
will be showing this statement
many different times with
different sections of it bolded
each to each time as we go
through. So here we're talking
about designing our projects
that empower others to
collaborate with inclusive
communities, but specifically
the design that we're thinking
about here. And the other.
Off the word slide
that will become very familiar
here is the, like I mentioned
earlier, focus on the design
within the Mozilla open
leadership framework. So we're
talking about helping people
understand, share, and
participate and feel included.
But I will get on to what the
open Canvas actually is, which
is perhaps the most exciting bit
of this. So it looks something
like this, we have a link, I
think it's in the probably in
the hack MD notes, you'll be
able to see a link to that. And
what this does is it provides
you a really structured way to
think about what the products
that you're creating is and the
community that will be involved,
both contributing and consuming
it. And moving on to the next
slide, here are some examples,
we can talk through this a
little bit more. So you can work
through this in a sort of nice
little flow way to think about
the things but if you get stuck
on any given box, it's also okay
to skip one and then come back
to it later. So looking at top
left, we talk about the top
problem or problems that you
want to solve with a project
that you're working on. So if I
was to do this, for example, for
lls, the top problem we might
want to solve would be the lack
of openness in the scientific
community. Their solution for
this, you think about what the
solution and again, if there's
more than one problem, you might
want to put more than one item
in this box. For or less I guess
our answer to solving the
problem will be to create a
program that allows other people
to learn more about openness,
and also to share it with
others, then how will we measure
success? And since I'm doing
this on the fly for lls I'm
almost in a minor panic here,
what do I how do we how do we
measure our level of success,
I'll say given that we have a
much bigger cohort for round to
the round one that this looks
like some measure of success, if
we look at counting the number
of people who are participating.
And the number of mentors and
experts that we have on board,
if we keep on seeing that climb,
or at least remain the same
rather than shrink, and I think
we are doing really well. For
your projects, this will
obviously be something else.
resources required. So this
might be that you need people's
time, it might be that you need
technical support, it might be
skills that you need, it might
be infrastructure, it might be
lab space, there are a lot of
different things that actually
the resources that you might be
looking for could be really
depends on what your project is.
And then moving on from here,
you start thinking, Okay, so
this is roughly what I want to
design. And now let's start
thinking about the people. And
so you can start thinking about
the contribution profiles. And
so this will be people who are
actually helping out with what
you're doing. And you want to
think who they are, what they
might like to do, how they might
like to contribute. And like we
mentioned earlier, you may want
to be thinking about the people
who have the expertise that came
from the resources required
section. And then you start
thinking about the user profile.
So these are the people who are
actually consuming what you're
creating these may be the same
people, as the contributors, or
they may be other people, it
really depends on what you're
designing. And then you also
start thinking about the
channels. So now that you know
the people that you're going to
be working with both people
creating the work and the people
who are consuming it, you start
thinking about how you will get
this new contributions and how
to get the new users and again,
it's okay, if these groups
overlap as well as you don't
have, they might be distinct
people or they might not. And
once you've thought through all
of those, maybe you have a
unique value proposition. So
this is perhaps reflecting back
on that vision as the the
statement that we've just been
working on. Maybe you want to
tweak it, or maybe you just want
to bring that mission and vision
statement right in here. And I
remember I was asked to do this,
I sort of thought okay, this
looks a bit tedious. But by the
time it actually worked through
what I could put in each box and
discussed it with my mentor, I
found it really useful, like I
thought really critically about
my project and the things and
the people that needed to bring
on board. So I would highly
recommend spending some time
thinking about this and going
through it with other people.
And if you're not sure bouncing
it off other people like maybe
in the iOS chat, for example is
a really good way to help you
think critically through the
best that you might be
struggling with. Okay, I think
it's gonna ask me on my slides
to walk through on all the stuff
that I've just done. But I'll
use that as a moment to have a
really quick recap. So left
side, we're talking about the
thing that we're creating right
side, we'll be talking about the
people talking about the
problems, we want to solve the
solution on the way that we that
you want to apply to that
problem, the ways to measure
their success. And then thinking
about the resources that you
need to get there. Once again,
think about the contributor
profiles, what types of
contributors and what sort of
personalities, people
backgrounds, they may have.
But I'm going to skip that
slide, because I'm not sure what
to say about that one. And then
also think about your users, and
the channels that you may have
to get them. Yeah, I'm just
gonna stop repeating this,
because I think I went through
it when I was just looking at
the next slide. And here, we
also have an example open canvas
here that is looking about
contribution ship badges for
science. So this is just working
through some of the demos, for
example, as well. So if you look
at the top, we're looking at
lack of recognition for certain
contribution types. And the
solution here was to give people
badges to gamify it. And so in
this case, the metrics that we
had was a number of publishers
using the badges and the number
of badges rewarded. And the
bottom left, you can see some of
the resources, you can say
someone said, we're going to use
some free hardware, a Heroku
process. And that's just the
type of server. They've taught
that they also need resources to
develop this to design this, and
also networking resources. So
publishers and orchids people
who are going to buy in to
actually using these batches, so
some of the different types of
resources you might need. Moving
over to the Community Profiles.
So that's on the left, we've got
contributions might be
developers, at publishers and at
orchids. And then also that you
have researchers who care about
the idea of these contributions
and maybe wants to code or want
to get the badges. moving
upwards, one box, you can see
the user profile, the use will
be publishers, researchers, and
once again, it might be awkward.
And then the channels for these
people, you're looking at a buy
in from an employer. So it's I
guess, if you want these badges
to measure, then you probably
want your employees to care
about the badges as well as this
is thinking critically about
who's going to be contributing
and how, as well as users who
and who may want new features.
And then you can reflect back on
to the user profiles as to who
those users are. And then we
have some user channels. And
this is looking mostly at social
media, and it talks at ways to
get these people. And then
finally moving all the way back
up to the top the top right
square, we have a unique value
profit proposition after having
thought through this. So the
unique value is issuing badges
to credit office. And that the
author roles may also be on your
papers. And so these are the
reasons that people might want
to buy into this. So I hope
hopefully that sort of
elucidates how the open Canvas
can help you think through a
given problem. And if you wish
to run your own open Canvas,
there's also a short link here
bitch dot L y flash or LS dash
open dash Canvas, but I think
there's probably a link in the
handy notes as well.